<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Pelican Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/anarchism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2011-10-22T00:54:00Z</updated><entry><title>Game Theory &amp; The Occupy Movement</title><link href="/game-theory-the-occupy-movement.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-10-22T00:54:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-10-22:game-theory-the-occupy-movement.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The global Occupy Movement in its current incarnation can be
characterised quite accurately in terms of a War of Attrition, to use
evolutionary game theoretic terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the starting point of evolutionary game theory, the first game
analysed by Maynard Smiths was called Hawk and Dove. In this game, two
contestants vie over a sharable resource. The two correspondent
strategies are that of Hawk and Dove. To play the Hawk is to display
aggressive behaviours, then escalate the competition for the resource
until either the Hawk wins or else is injured. Dove's strategy in the
game is to first make a show of aggression, but, when faced with
escalation to physical violence, will turn heel and run away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the payoff matrix for the Hawk / Dove game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/hawkdove.jpeg" title="hawkdove" /&gt;][]So, War of Attrition -- cool name, right? War of Attrition is
identical to the Hawk and Dove scenario, albeit that the resource is
&lt;em&gt;deemed unsharable&lt;/em&gt;. So in the above scenario where either two Hawks or
two Doves vie, the desired resource is divided in accordance with the
payoff matrix. But in War of Attrition, this sharing or splitting of
resources is no longer an option, and so the violently aggressive
behaviours associated with the Hawk / Dove game are no longer effective
strategies. Instead, in War of Attrition, two new strategies, known as
Bluffer and Bourgeois emerge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A safer strategy of display, bluffing and waiting to win, then becomes
viable – a Bluffer strategy. The game then becomes one of accumulating
costs, either the costs of displaying or costs of prolonged unresolved
engagement. It’s effectively an auction; the winner is the contestant
who will swallow the greater cost while the loser gets, for all his
pains, the same cost as the winner but NO resource. The resulting
evolutionary game theory mathematics leads to an optimal strategy of
timed bluffing, where any player backs off with equal probability at
any time in the contest - unguessable by his opponent. This is exactly
what is observed in nature for contests in a number of species, for
example between male dung flies contesting for mating sites. The
timing of disengagement in these contests follows the exact
mathematical curve derived from the evolutionary theory mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a mutant strategy which can better that of Bluffer in the War
of Attrition Game. This is the Bourgeois strategy (Maynard Smith named
the strategy Bourgeois, because with his background of communism he
regarded it as “politically bourgeois” way to value ownership).
Bourgeois uses an asymmetry of some sort to break the deadlock. In
nature one such asymmetry is possession - which contestant has the
prior possession of the resource. The strategy is to play a Hawk if in
possession of the resource, but to display then retreat if not in
possession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one takes a look at the &lt;a href="http://web.mit.edu/rpindyck/www/Courses/GT_05a.pdf"&gt;Collusive and Nash Equilibriums for the War
of Attrition&lt;/a&gt;, it is clear that costs are exorbitantly high to both
players involved. However, payoff in terms of resources in this game is
&lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; maximized for the Collusive Equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise that last paragraph might be gobbledegook to some. Basically,
what this means is that if both people stand around bluffing for a long
time, or, even worse, if one just sits on an unshared resource and the
other one randomly runs up and puts on a show of dissent or aggression,
nothing's going to get done. There will be high costs to both parties in
the long run. It would be better for the two parties to collude and thus
share the "unsharable" resource.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the Occupy Movement, I think you understand where I'm going. We
have a class of bourgeois dining on balconies and drinking champagne,
while staring down at a bunch of rabble-rousing protesters with tents on
Wall St. We have one group who is sitting smugly on a pile of ill-used
resources, and another group who is quite literally putting on a show of
aggression for the former. Now, the occupation is non-violent, we all
know this. And thus, the former group knows that this show is a bluff.
Nothing will happen. They can sit there drinking their champagne all
day, and nothing is going to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hey, Occupiers! &lt;em&gt;Guess what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bluffing is not an effective strategy.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/hawkdove.jpeg" title="hawkdove" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/hawkdove.jpeg&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Distractions</title><link href="/distractions.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-10-04T22:55:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-10-04:distractions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Physics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: Why are quantum physicists so poor at sex?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Because when they find the position, they can't find the momentum,
and when they have the momentum, they can't find the position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heisenberg went for a drive and got stopped by a traffic cop. The cop
asked, "Do you know how fast you were going?" Heisenberg replied, "No,
but I know where I am."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many theoretical physicists specializing in general relativity
does it take to change a light bulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Two. One to hold the bulb and one to rotate the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is this farmer who is having problems with his chickens. All of
the sudden, they are all getting very sick and he doesn't know what is
wrong with them. After trying all conventional means, he calls a
biologist, a chemist, and a physicist to see if they can figure out what
is wrong. So the biologist looks at the chickens, examines them a bit,
and says he has no clue what could be wrong with them. Then the chemist
takes some tests and makes some measurements, but he can't come to any
conclusions either. So the physicist tries. He stands there and looks at
the chickens for a long time without touching them or anything. Then all
of the sudden he starts scribbling away in a notebook. Finally, after
several gruesome calculations, he exclaims, 'I've got it! But it only
works for spherical chickens in a vacuum.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A student recognizes Einstein in a train and asks: Excuse me, professor,
but does New York stop at this train?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers in Fairbanks Alaska announced last week that they have
discovered a superconductor which will operate at room temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychopathic Physics Test:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: A shotgun shooting 12 pellets of 00 Buckshot weighing 4g leave the
barrel at 1125 fps. Assuming the average infant will absorb 127.3 f/lbs
before disintegrating, how many babies will the average blast cut
through (rounding off to the nearest whole number)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: eight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: A 100 kg man is being swung by his entrails in a circle 16'in radius
at the rate of 1600 radians/sec. Find the tension in the man's entrails
(ignoring the effects of gravity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: 65,024 Newtons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: A pagan priest attempts to vaporize a young virgin by placing her in
a flaming pit. Assuming the woman, weighing 120 lbs, is completely
composed of water, how much energy will he have to use to completely
vaporize her?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: 130,000 BTU&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: An infant has a tensile strength of 400 psi and has a cross sectional
area of 23.4 sq. inches. Assuming it is 23" long and has an elongation
percentage of .0036%/120psi at roomtemperature, how long will the baby
be before it is dismembered?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: about 26.45 inches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: A 12 year old blind orphan girl is shot from a cannon at the speed of
1200 fps at a solid brick wall. Calculate the force of impact given that
the brick wall is 3 feet away from the barrel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: If she weighs 50 lbs, and all of her sticks to the wall, 3.3 million
Newtons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: A large plane weighing 12.7 M tons carrying 12 tons of nuns and
orphans travelling at 724.46 kph and at an altitude of 40,000 meters
suffers explosive decompression above the center of a 30km diameter
population. Assuming that one passenger is sucked out every second, how
many passengers will land within the population center?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: about (give or take a torso or leg) 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: A 1000 lb car is moving at 130 mph and two poodles whose combined
weight is 82 lbs are thrown out the back at 3 mph. Calculate the
velocity of the car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: 140.91 happy mph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;anarchism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: Why do they bury cops six feet under?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Because deep down they're really good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: What's the difference between a porcupine and a cop car?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: The porcupine has its pricks on the outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How do you make a cop sound like a dog?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Pour gas and light a match. WOOF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How do you make a cop cry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Throw back the teargas canister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: What's the worst thing about a squad car with two cops in it driving
off a cliff?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Squad cars seat at least four.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many insurrectionist anarchists does it take to change a
lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: The lightbulb cannot be changed, it must be smashed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many crust punks does it take to change a lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: There's change in a lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many tree-sitters does it take to screw in a lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Tree-sitters don't screw in lightbulbs, silly; they screw in trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many individualist anarchists does it take to change a lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: One.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many hipsters does it take to screw in a lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Ah, it's a really obscure number, man...you wouldn't know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: How many vegans does it take to screw in a lightbulb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: I don't know, but where do you get your protein?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: Why did the primitivist move to Eugene?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: He heard there was no work there.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="anarchism"></category></entry><entry><title>Science Without Hierarchy</title><link href="/science-without-hierarchy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-09-29T09:12:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-09-29:science-without-hierarchy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bmartin.cc/pubs/94raven.html"&gt;This is an interesting piece&lt;/a&gt; on what science might look like after
an anarchist revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is depressingly 1980s in its perceptions of developing
action within modern scientific theory (specifically the section on
Anarchist Epistemology, which states, &lt;em&gt;"Paul Feyerabend is the most
prominent philosopher to champion a different philosophy of science. He
criticises the positivist, dogmatic approach to knowledge that is common
in establishment science, in which almost all resources are devoted to
exploring the implications of the dominant theoretical framework. He
supports, instead, investigation of a range of competing theories. This
is called 'anarchist' because there is no central theoretical dogma that
dictates scientific research [[13]][].&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry, and maybe it's just within the physics community, but I would
like to point out that General Relativity and the Standard Model are the
currently accepted theories, while most papers I read are challenges or
modifications to one or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article also disappoints with its appeals to allow the opinions of
non-scientists to have &lt;em&gt;as much&lt;/em&gt; weight as those of scientists. Should
the opinions of outside entities count? Yes. Of course. Everyone should
have a say in the development of things which effect the community as a
whole. But -- and I'll apologize again -- sorry,
hippie-bro-dude-number-387-who-smokes-too-much-DMT, you don't fucking
get to tell me about your theory of how Atlantean sacred geometry causes
pressure to equal gravitation. Go sell Hollywood your idea, because I
sure as hell am not interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahem. There were some positive points, especially the author's clear
elucidation of the separation of society and the scientific communities,
and how this ideological framework restricts positive change:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This set of directions for an anarchist science policy implies a
dramatic shift in the present social context of science: many research
topics would be different, communities rather than powerful
institutions would support and control the scientific enterprise, many
more people would participate in research, and everyone could be
involved in making science policy. Such a change is unlikely without
similar changes in other aspects of society. Indeed, it has long been
my opinion that science is one of the social institutions most
resistant to popular participation and control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even radical critics of science have seldom explored the implications
of self-management. Critics of science are prone to reject science
itself. Science is seen as either good, neutral or bad, in each case
having an essence that is independent of society. A more useful
perspective for radicals is to see science as a feature or aspect of
society, currently mainly oriented to the requirements of elites but
with potentials for development to be a useful part of a society
without hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite different from the idea that science is neutral and can
be 'used' for good purposes or 'abused' for bad purposes. This is like
saying that 'the economy' (that is, the current capitalist economy)
can be used or abused, to produce food or weapons. This use-abuse
model ignores the possibility of other economic systems or other
science systems. As I've indicated, various aspects of science could
be potentially be changed: research directions, institutional context,
participation in research, decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[[13]]: http://www.bmartin.cc/pubs/94raven.html#fn13&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="anarchism"></category><category term="epistemology"></category><category term="post-revolution"></category><category term="science"></category></entry><entry><title>Trivialities, Time Travel, and Justified Rage</title><link href="/trivialities-time-travel-and-justified-rage.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-09-26T18:22:00Z</updated><author><name>isis</name></author><id>tag:,2011-09-26:trivialities-time-travel-and-justified-rage.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is rather trivial, but I wanted to point out this amazing song by
dark synthpop artist &lt;a href="http://mausspace.com/"&gt;John Maus&lt;/a&gt; about killing cops:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, to make it even better, Maus is currently pursuing a Ph.D. in
Political Philosophy at the European Graduate School in Switzerland. I
really enjoy when other academia come out and directly say that our
current system of hierarchy and oppression is fucked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as if Maus wasn't awesome enough after that, he's also got a song
about time travel, complete with the classic goth
whip-crack-as-a-crash-symbol:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\&amp;lt;3 \&amp;lt;3 \&amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="academia"></category><category term="Anarchism"></category><category term="fuck tha police"></category><category term="gothic"></category><category term="John Maus"></category><category term="time travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Anarcho-Transhumanism: The Death of Sexism</title><link href="/anarcho-transhumanism-the-death-of-sexism.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-09-23T00:51:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-09-23:anarcho-transhumanism-the-death-of-sexism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anarcho-transhumanism. Is much better than being a sexist biological
essentialist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as [Will just pointed out, it means sexist and biological
essential arguments lose any grounding they might have had][] because
bodies become the creations of their inhabitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Men are \&amp;lt;insert biological essentialist bullshit here&gt;, and women are
\&amp;lt;insert more essentialist crap&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is a man? And what even is a woman? If our bodies have been
altered beyond recognition, with cybernetic appendages, brain-machine
interfaces,  and nanorobotic-enhanced immune systems, can you honestly
continue to make ill-founded claims about the effects of my having a
clitoris? Or what about when I gene-hack my sequences, adding in bits of
exogenic, interspecies, or designer DNA? Are you really going to say
that the person with cephalopodic integument is "more emotional" because
they decided to keep their human vagina? &lt;em&gt;Puh-lease.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Will just pointed out, it means sexist and biological essential
  arguments lose any grounding they might have had]: https://humaniterations.wordpress.com/2011/09/21/the-floating-metal-sphere-trump-card/#respond&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Every Anarchist Should Be A Scientist</title><link href="/every-anarchist-should-be-a-scientist.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-09-10T22:41:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-09-10:every-anarchist-should-be-a-scientist.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My friend William says that &lt;a href="https://humaniterations.wordpress.com/2011/08/10/every-scientist-should-be-an-anarchist/"&gt;all scientists should be anarchists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he's right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I should also add that &lt;em&gt;all anarchists should be scientists&lt;/em&gt;, at
least to some extent. We should never allow ourselves to become so rigid
as to forget what makes us anarchists in the first place: childlike
curiosity, incessant inquiry, and a radical love for taking things to
their roots to further our understanding. We seek to dismantle the world
around us, knowing that it does not function as well as it could. We
want to understand ourselves, our environment, and each other. We want
the blueprints for the social machine, so we can sledgehammer the fuck
out of it, and build it back up from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what that sounds like? That sounds like science. And that
&lt;a href="http://www.mithral.com/~beberg/manifesto.html"&gt;sounds like hacking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anarchists are radicals, and I shouldn't need to point out for the
zillionth time that radicalism means taking things down to the roots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, anarchists &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; scientists, even if some resign to mere social
science. Anarchists are hackers, even if in some cases that only goes as
far as hacking up an herbal tincture for a sick friend. Their walls
cannot stop us; there are infinite possible paths around and under and
even through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"This is our world now... the world of the electron and the switch, the
beauty of the baud. We make use of a service already existing without
paying for what could be dirt-cheap if it wasn't run by profiteering
gluttons, and you call us criminals. We explore... and you call us
criminals. We seek after knowledge... and you call us criminals. We
exist without skin color, without nationality, without religious bias...
and you call us criminals. You build atomic bombs, you wage wars, you
murder, cheat, and lie to us and try to make us believe it's for our own
good, yet we're the criminals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, I am a criminal. My crime is that of curiosity. My crime is that
of judging people by what they say and think, not what they look like.
My crime is that of outsmarting you, something that you will never
forgive me for.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I am a hacker, and this is my manifesto. You may stop this individual,
but you can't stop us all...&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Primitivists: GTFO!</title><link href="/primitivists-gtfo.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-08-29T22:02:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-08-29:primitivists-gtfo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The coupling of anarchism and primitivism within modern radical
discourse needs to be entirely deconstructed. First, I would like to
point out the obvious and inherent logical fallacies in this coalescence
of, on the one hand, an array of social movements whose sole unifying
ideological standpoint is an opposition to unequal power dynamics, and
on the other hand, a socio-cultural movement which openly advocates
biological essentialism, which translates to &lt;a href="http://veganideal.org/content/lierre-keith-case-study-anti-trans-hatred"&gt;insubstantiation of fluid
gender identities&lt;/a&gt; and other such destructions of personal freedom,
and the abolition of human creativity and inquiry through the "moral
obligation" for humans to "fill their niche" within a biosphere. This is
not even mentioning other troublesome logic within the primitivist
discourse, which I won't touch upon here, but will simply say, "Yo,
dudes, ever heard of this thing called the &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Naturalistic_fallacy"&gt;naturalistic fallacy&lt;/a&gt;?
It's closely tied to other problematic and illogical argument forms like
&lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Appeal_to_nature#Rational_argument"&gt;appeal to nature&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Appeal_to_tradition"&gt;appeal to tradition&lt;/a&gt;...wait, were you
calling yourselves anarchists? Anarchists making &lt;em&gt;appeals to tradition&lt;/em&gt;.
Yeah. Okay." Get the fuck out of my movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm concerned with freedom, not anthropocentrically, but f&lt;a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/godwin/"&gt;reedom in a
broader sense of a maximization of informed agency&lt;/a&gt;, which includes
taking into context the environment we all share. That's right, I said
it. I care about the trees; I care about the non-human and human
animals; I care about the cyborgs and the robots and the AIs. To quote
&lt;a href="https://queersingularity.wordpress.com/2011/06/26/transhumanism-and-the-radical-left-anarchist-skillshare-2011/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Queering the Singularity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: "Outside of hierarchy, a diversity of
legitimate life arrangements exist. We need a radical coalition capable
united action against the oppressors and a future vision that embraces
both reaching for the stars and returning to the woods."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don't care about you, primitivists. Can't you see that my way
still allows you to opt-out and go live in the woods? It's not the
scientists who are the enemy here, it's the goddamned State. So get the
fuck out, you primitivists, &lt;a href="https://guerrillanews.wordpress.com/2011/08/17/anti-nanotech-bomb-claim-by-individualists-tending-towards-the-wild-mexico/"&gt;you who go around bombing nanotechnology
research centers&lt;/a&gt;, too blinded by your dogma to understand that
nanofabrication would provide methods of materials production while
drastically reducing mining and logging. If you can build atoms and
molecules from the particles up, why mine coal when you could literally
grow it in a lab? No, this isn't science fiction; welcome to the 21st
century. And why do you persist in subservience to "natural"
limitations? We need to look at what we are capable of, rather than rely
on frequency analysis of events. Yes, humans are, more often than not,
born as either male or female. Yes, governments cover every scrap of dry
land. But none of these have to be the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, your leader: &lt;a href="http://vancouver.mediacoop.ca/audio/deep-green-resistance-death-threats-and-police/8014"&gt;Yeah, he's cooperating with the FBI&lt;/a&gt;. Y'all were
saying something? Wait. I can't hear you. All I'm hearing is "We're a
bunch of fascistic, heteronormative, and illogical scum."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to cut this short because Donna Haraway rather elegantly
postulated (minus the socialist portions) my position twenty years ago
in &lt;a href="https://www.stanford.edu/dept/HPS/Haraway/CyborgManifesto.html"&gt;"A Cyborg Manifesto"&lt;/a&gt;. Read it. It's good. It's really, really
good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously, read &lt;a href="https://www.stanford.edu/dept/HPS/Haraway/CyborgManifesto.html"&gt;"A Cyborg Manifesto"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Strive to Survive</title><link href="/strive-to-survive.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-07-04T18:28:00Z</updated><author><name>isis</name></author><id>tag:,2011-07-04:strive-to-survive.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/anarquismo7.jpg" title="anarquisma" /&gt;][]You don't have to have much of a theoretical understanding of
politics to understand that coercion is ethically wrong. Basically, the
argument goes like this: The creative and intellectual capacity of a
conscious agent is directly proportional to their available degrees of
freedom. Thus, the more options an individual has available to them, the
better they are able to operate. Coercion restricts degrees of freedom
by forcing the agent into a predetermined path of action. Anything which
unnecessarily restricts freedom by coercion is inefficient and a
detriment to the overall creative and intellectual capacity of the
species, and thereby is an existential risk to the species, and thereby
should be considered ethically wrong. The state does not ask the citizen
if they wish to be a citizen, it tells them so. There is no other
option, and thus the state is intrinsically coercive, and thus ethically
wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this day and age, it's probably going to take extremely responsible
use of high technology to guarantee the survival of humankind. We're not
going to be able to simply go back to being hunter-gatherers --
lackadaisically wonderful as that would be -- there's too many people,
and anyone who says over 6 billion need to die for their survival is an
egotistical, un-empathetic piece of shit. So we're stuck with
technology. And we and other species are stuck on this planet, for now,
so we need to also take care of it. But that technology bit: high
technology is best imagined, developed, and engineered by unfettered
minds. Thus, a highly technological anarchist society is the best
guarantee for humankind's survival. The state is killing us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you're free to disagree with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\&amp;lt;(A)3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/anarquismo7.jpg" title="anarquisma" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/anarquismo7.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Game Theory &amp; anarchism II: How information can smash the state</title><link href="/game-theory-anarchism-ii-how-information-can-smash-the-state.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-08T04:39:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-06-08:game-theory-anarchism-ii-how-information-can-smash-the-state.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Playing The Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's play a game. This game, called “&lt;a href="http://mindyourdecisions.com/blog/2008/03/18/game-theory-tuesdays-winning-a-%E2%80%9Cbeauty-contest%E2%80%9D-or-how-my-professor-gambled-250-teaching-a-lesson/"&gt;Guess Two Thirds of the
Average&lt;/a&gt;” is usually one of the first games that students of game
theory are exposed to. The game works like this: There is a room full of
people, and each is asked to choose a number between zero and one
hundred. The winner is the person who chooses the number which is two
thirds of the average of everyone else's numbers combined. So, if
everyone else picks one hundred, and you chose sixty-six, you would win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's an &lt;a href="http://museumofmoney.org/exhibitions/games/guessnumber2.htm"&gt;interactive flash applet of the game&lt;/a&gt;, which you can play
with other people online to get an idea of how this game plays out in
the general population. You might want to check that out before I go any
farther in explaining the theory of how the game should be played
through a purely rational or superrational strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, obviously, all numbers sixty-seven and above are automatically ruled
out as possible solutions. However, what if &lt;em&gt;the other players&lt;/em&gt; are
clever enough to also realize this? Well, that's simple then: you can
assume that no one else will choose anything over sixty-six, and
therefore the maximum number you should pick is two thirds of that, so
forty-four. But wait! Just &lt;em&gt;how clever&lt;/em&gt; are these other players? Have
they realized this as well? Because if they have, you shouldn't guess
above twenty-nine. Oh jeepers, these &lt;em&gt;other players&lt;/em&gt; could be really
smart, like &lt;a href="http://www.math.ubc.ca/~hauert/research/gamelab/twothirds.html"&gt;math nerds&lt;/a&gt; or something. They could be doing all the
same meta-processing as you're doing. Better not guess above nineteen...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be a purely rational strategy, and taken to its logical
conclusion, it clearly rules out all numbers except zero. However, if
you played around with the applet above, you already know that the
winning number for the game played within a sector of the general
population (read: not math nerds) is much higher – in some cases as high
as twenty-four (I think that one was conducted at a liberal arts
college...). So, if we look at each level of processing in the purely
rational strategy, we can label them as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0º : 66.67 (It's the zeroth-degree of processing because...well, you'd
literally have to have rocks in your head to not get at least that
level.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1º : 44.45&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2º : 29.63&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3º : 19.75&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4º : 13.17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5º : 8.78&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6º : 5.85&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7º : 3.90&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8º : 2.60&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9º : 1.73&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10º: 1.16&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11º: 0.77&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12º: 0.51&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13º: 0.34&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it is statistically shown that the general human population
is incapable of rational thought for more than three successive
iterations. My first thought at this was: “Grumble, grumble...and I
thought humans could be intelligent enough to forego government.” It's
like, even more demoralizing than anarchist in-fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there's good news. (And, there is also &lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/The-Possibility-of-Cooperation-Michael-Taylor.zip"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Possibility of
Cooperation&lt;/em&gt; (.pdf.zip)&lt;/a&gt;, an anarchist game theory textbook by Michael
Taylor.) You see, I realized, and plenty of other people have realized,
including the United States government, that the general population's
lack of rationality can be exploited. Now, I equivocate here (“Faith,
here's an equivocator, that could / swear in both the scales against
either scale, who com- / mitted treason enough for God's sake, yet could
/ not equivocate to heaven. O, come in, equivocator.” - Shakespeare,
Macbeth, 2.3.8-10); let me clarify. There are two uses which immediately
bear to mind concerning exploitation of irrationality: the first, for
purposes of subjugation and control, and the second, for information
analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Predicting The Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier, in &lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/2011/01/game-theory-anarchism-why-snitches-are-snitches-and-why-anarchists-are-not-snitches/"&gt;my first Game Theory &amp;amp; anarchism piece&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned
Douglas Hofstader's concept of superrationality, that a player of games
takes into consideration a broader contextual analysis of both the game
and the other players' strategies in order to formulate their own
strategy. In light of the concept of superrationality, the general
population's abrupt halt at meta-processing level three – instead of
being interpreted as qualitative proof of human stupidity – can rather
be viewed as proof of humans &lt;em&gt;assuming&lt;/em&gt;human stupidity and altering
their actions based upon this judgment. To spell it out in plaintext in
case you didn't catch that: humans will generally assume that other
humans are irrational, and so suspend their own rationality to act on a
common level. Thus, superrationality is a prediction of the level of
meta-processing power of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving back to the information analysis bit, this prediction can become
a tool when applied on a mass scale. Take the stock market, for example.
Traders ultimately base their calculations not on how financially well
they believe Evil, Inc. is going to do, but on how financially well
&lt;em&gt;other traders&lt;/em&gt; think Evil, Inc. is going to do. The stock market is not
strictly a financial market, but an information market detailing
predictions of human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I go into some really wonderful potentials for &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Prediction_markets"&gt;predictive
markets&lt;/a&gt;, let me briefly outline some really terrible ones. As I said,
this is a tool; a pickaxe is neither intrinsically good nor bad. You can
mine coal with it, or kill Trotsky with it...okay, both of those might
be bad, but you get my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rigging The Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.palantirtech.com"&gt;Palantir Technologies&lt;/a&gt; is a corporation based in the silicon valley
which offers extremely powerful informational analytics engines to
government and financial institutions. This technology is being used to
scour databases – everything from Twitter to employment records – to
ultimately determine who knows who, what everyone is doing, and what
groups contain which members. The user interface for their program is
highly impressive, featuring keyword searching and geographical
overlays. Put simply, this is very bad news for political and civil
rights activists. With this software, an intelligence agent can simply
type the keyword “anarchist” into the user interface, zoom in on any
given city, and be presented with a map of who is likely to be an
anarchist and the statistical probability of their being so, where they
are believed to live or work, and who they are likely involved with. Bad
news fucking bears. However, at the risk of sounding like a broken
record, this is a tool, and is not “bad” &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;. This same software,
if obtained by activists, could be used to route out undercover agents
within the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Palantir's software is not, strictly speaking, an information market;
it's only information analysis. However, another similar company,
&lt;a href="https://www.recordedfuture.com/"&gt;Recorded Futures&lt;/a&gt;, is claiming that it can use, for all intents and
purposes, the same information databases and heuristic models to predict
the future. Why stop at knowing the identities of the black bloc
yesterday when you can know what their identities will be next week?
Perhaps it's worth mentioning that &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/dangerroom/2010/07/exclusive-google-cia/"&gt;their two largest investors are
Google and the CIA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2003, DARPA publicly announced their own &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Policy_Analysis_Market"&gt;Policy Analysis Market&lt;/a&gt;,
appropriately nicknamed the &lt;a href="http://www.au.af.mil/au/awc/awcgate/nps/pam/si_pam.htm"&gt;Terrorism Market&lt;/a&gt;, in which traders' bets
would be used to predict the likelihood of various political actions in
the Middle East, such as the probability of the United States recalling
its troops from Saudi Arabia or Egyptian currency falling by 20% by the
end of the year. Controversially, and the subject of mass media outcry,
the original plan for the Policy Analysis Market also included
predictions for the probabilities, and dates of, assassinations of
public figures. Which is where we now get into the really wonderful uses
of this tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hacking The Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Jim_Bell"&gt;Jim Bell&lt;/a&gt;, a crypto-anarchist and MIT graduate, wrote a famous essay
back in the day called &lt;a href="http://jya.com/ap.htm"&gt;“Assassination Markets”&lt;/a&gt;. I remember reading
it on my home-built PC in grade school and having my little mind blown
to smithereens. (Oh, the potentials! Oh, so dark! Oh, so radical!)
Anyway. In that essay, Bell outlines a system, using currently available
encryption and privacy methods (such as &lt;a href="http://www.gnupg.org/"&gt;PGP&lt;/a&gt; generated asymmetric
keys, online anonymous currencies like &lt;a href="http://www.bitcoin.org/"&gt;BitCoin&lt;/a&gt;, and networks like
&lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/.onion"&gt;Tor Hidden Services&lt;/a&gt;), for people to place online, completely
anonymous, bets on the precise date and time of a government official's
death. The person who guesses correctly collects all the money. This
ceases to be a pure prediction market, and crosses over into real life,
becoming an assassination market: the winner is (most likely, although
of course, not provably) the assassin, and everyone else who
purposefully bet wrongly is merely donating the in the amount that they
would like to see said official dead. Of course, none of this is
provable in any way, and for details of how the system would be set up
you should read the original paper. Even the people running the server
which hosts the assassination market would be incapable of giving out
any data on the assassin if requested to or if subpoenaed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim Bell is now currently in prison. The original offense was
“harassment of a federal agent”. However, if you take a closer look at
the story, Bell claimed that federal agents were stalking him, and they
in turn claimed that he was stalking them and thereby charged him with
harassment. He got out in 2009, but was taken in again in 2010 for
violation of parole. I'm sure his parole conditions read something like
“Thou shalt not so much as look at a computer...” Bastards. Jim Bell did
other awesome things though, before they entrapped him. Somewhere in the
'90s, in Portland, Oregon, he was part of the Multnomah County Common
Law Court, which had no judicial authority according to federal laws,
and which put government officials on trial &lt;em&gt;in absentia&lt;/em&gt; and relegated
judgments and sentences against them accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for the doublepluscool part, and the reason why I've been setting
all this up. Though I'm sure I lost half the anarchist milieu at the
mention of mathematics, and half the math geeks at the mention of
crypto-anarchism, that still leaves an estimated two people reading
this. So it might be intellectual masturbation, but I'd like to take a
look into applications of superrationality to assassination markets as
part of a broader study of how such a market might function, what
impediments may present themselves, and if such a market can be
considered moral in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I go any further in my explorations of such a dangerous idea, I
would like to plainly state that my interest is purely academic, and
give the following reasons. My overall goal in life can be summarized
as: I would like to live to see the creation of a technologically
advanced anarchist society. While with a cursory glance this may appear
as motivation to develop an assassination market, it also presents
several obstacles. I'll go through the obstacles in order of words in
the original statement. First, &lt;em&gt;I would like to live&lt;/em&gt;. I believe if an
assassination market were to be effectuated, political leaders could
retaliate by pooling bets against those involved in sustaining the
existence of that market. I'm not suicidal. Second, &lt;em&gt;technological
advancement&lt;/em&gt; requires broader sociocultural backing and support for its
development, and using computer technology for such morally ambiguous
ends could result in a shift towards greater fear of technological
advancement. Technology should be ultimately used for the good of all
people, with respect for the environment we share. Lastly, my
interpretation of the phrase &lt;em&gt;anarchist society&lt;/em&gt; is a world in which
there are no leaders, where individuals' capacities for informed agency
for action is maximized as a whole. Obviously, murder reduces one's
agency to zero. Note that I said “as a whole”: murder can be acceptable,
provided that the person who is murdered was taking extreme actions to
limit the degrees of freedom of others. In this way, freedom as a whole
is maximized. However, an assassination market would be begging to be
abused in any number of ways, and I cannot foresee that agency and
freedom would always be maximized. Thus, the following thought
experiments are purely academic, as I'm not assured of the morality of
actualizing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I would like to point out that there is an &lt;a href="http://4eiruntyxxbgfv7o.onion"&gt;"assassination
market" on Tor already&lt;/a&gt;. (Note: you must be connected to the Tor
network to view .onion sites. If you're unsure about your Tor
configuration, don't know what Tor is, or otherwise don't know what
you're doing, &lt;em&gt;please don't click that link&lt;/em&gt;.) The problem with it is
that a contractor posts a mark, or an individual they wish doom and
gloom upon, and sets a price on their head. Then the "bidders"
anonymously (through TorPM) contact the contractor with a deathday
prediction, and if they are correct the contractor pays them the
previously set amount. From a user named "admin", it is explained that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Basically, you bet (using TorBank) on the day of a particular
individual's death. Once TorBank gets up, the forum will become active
for assassination bets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Procedure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​1. The contractor creates a thread with the details about the target,
payment amount, and contact information (TorPM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​2. The takers on the assassination bet will contact the contractor
through TorPM and will provide their TorBank information along with
the date that they predict the target will die on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​3. Once the target dies, the contractor looks through their TorPM
offers and identifies the contact who correctly predicted the death
date. The contact then gets paid through TorBank."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an assassination market. It's not a even a market. It's a
centralized and fatally untrustworthy system for hiring cold-blooded
killers. There are no true bets, there's just a price. And, furthermore,
the contractor isn't bound in any way to uphold the agreement -- they
could just as well run with the money after the job is done. Likewise,
the killer could merely kidnap the victim, bake cookies and have a tea
party in fancy dresses with them, claim they're dead and then split the
money with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That "assassination market" would be modeled as a non-iterative
Prisoner's Dilemma:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/game-a-market.png" title="Game Theory Analysis of Tor &amp;quot;Assassination Market&amp;quot;" /&gt;][]Which has the Nash equilibrium of mutual defection (the
contractor runs with the money, and the killer merely kidnaps), which is
Pareto sub-optimum. Same as the regular ol' Prisoner's Dilemma. The
greater problem in this scenario is that there is little or no
possibility for cooperation because it is not an iterated (i.e.
repeated) game. Because the users of this false "assassination market"
remain anonymous, as they should, there is the regrettable consequence
that there is no available mechanism for building reputation and trust.
Which is why, in Jim Bell's original proposal, trust is centralized in
the server hosting the market -- that way, if the server repeatedly
fails to deliver payments, trust is broken and no one will participate
in the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A potential problem in Bell's scheme is the intrinsic inaccuracy to the
information on the number of betters that the Assassination market
provides. That is, there is the possibility of a single entity, rather
than placing one bet for \$100,000,000, placing one hundred million bets
for \$1, which would skew the information in the market. Basically,
which looks sketchier: a single billionaire willing to put down on
someone's death, or a global community of people who all agree that
someone should die?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That problem arises from the very nature of anonymity: if you are
capable of being anonymous once, you're capable of being anonymous on
infinite separate occasions. The only solution I can imagine would be to
build some type of hardware, a handset device or something,
manufacturing one for every single person on the planet. Each handset
would be a personalized betting machine, i.e. it would be possible to
tell that a certain machine is making multiple bets, but not which
machine, among all the others, it is. However, this would embroil a slew
of new problems for the networking involved and uncountable security
issues that I don't even want to begin pondering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Lindorff, in &lt;em&gt;CounterPunch Newsletter&lt;/em&gt;, brings up another possible
skew scenario for assassination markets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"So we'd have to worry about people manipulating the terrorism futures
market, I guess. And how would you do that? Bet on a dramatic but
highly unlikely assassination, maybe, like the president of the United
States perhaps, or the terror bombing of a high-profile target like
Disney Land or the Chunnel. And then go out and finance the hit by
some willing terror cell. Such market manipulation would give a whole
new meaning to that Wall Street term 'making a killing.'"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem with this critique is that Lindorff apparently can't do
math. If a person were to bet such a large amount on an obscure event
(large enough that it would tip the market, meaning most of the money in
the market would be coming from that person), and then go out and pay
someone to cause the event, then they would simply get their money back,
plus a little extra from the market for having the correct prediction.
But &lt;em&gt;they lose all the money used to fund the event actually occurring&lt;/em&gt;.
Why would someone bother to use a prediction market in this context,
when no money would be made by doing so? Wouldn't it be simpler to just
fund the event?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is an excerpt from &lt;a href="http://www.anti-state.com/vroman/vroman9.html"&gt;a detailed and extensive response by
Robert Vroman&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.anti-state.com/murphy/murphy17.html"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.anti-state.com/young/young2.html"&gt;objections&lt;/a&gt; made against &lt;a href="http://www.anti-state.com/vroman/vroman8.html"&gt;his original
essay on the Bell Assassination Politics&lt;/a&gt; system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Murphy doubts the feasibility of AP with the very legitimate
concern that if the system were truly an impenetrable secret to all
investigators, there is nothing stopping the AP operators from
pocketing all the donations, yet claiming winners had been paid,
resting on the impossibility of discovery, and the robbed winner’s
desire to remain anonymous (since he’s probably got blood on his
hands). A better scam might involve creating artificially high
bounties, and then only paying out what’s actually in the pot. Since
if there are multiple bets on the same day, the prize is split evenly
between them, the assassin will not know if he has been cheated or if
there are actually were enough other random guessers to dilute his
prize down to the share he actually gets. The administrators could
also skim off a healthy chunk too, and no one would be the wiser. This
would probably be the best way to for the admins to dishonestly game
the system, so that they enrich themselves; the assassins are
disappointed but not given proof of treachery; and the bounties are
higher than normal, thus enticing more gullible thugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is this really a problem? Seems to me the system still works
exactly as planned whether the admins are honest or not. The only
problem is getting people to trust the system in the first place,
which I’ll cover in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we assume that the admins’ purpose in creating AP is to make as fat
a profit as possible, then they will not want to blatantly rip off hit
men, for fear that word will inevitably get out among the criminal
population that AP isn’t on the level. However, even in an extreme
case where the admins do embezzle every penny, it doesn’t matter.
Since very few people involved with AP will be actually killing
anyone, only a tiny minority of users will feel they have been
cheated, while the greater number will be convinced they got their
money’s worth. Thus they will continue to use the system. Future
assassins not in communication with their gypped colleagues will also
be led to believe others have been paid. Thus everything still works,
money goes in, prizes are accumulated, and targets are eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the admins really are capable of hiding all evidence and expertly
conning the system, then the system will indeed be conned, and so well
conned, that it will continue to run despite being conned over and
over. The only problem is if this possibility prevents people from
ever starting to bet and becoming convinced they are being dealt with
fairly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two answers to this: the AP business can slowly build trust
with less extreme versions of itself, and also the overlooked fact
that people have surprisingly high tolerance for potentially
fraudulent online services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To establish itself as an authentic operation, AP might be introduced
not as a full fledged death machine but instead as a low key betting
pool system whereby users could put money on sporting events or guess
the day certain celebrities will get divorced, and other trivial
wagers. The selling point is the hardcore anonyminity feature for
users in harsher nanny states. In this relatively low risk phase,
winners could have the option of being publicly announced for ego’s
sake, and this would prove the system operated as intended. Then
gradually more and more sinister bets would be allowed until it
becomes completely un-moderated and AP is born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a system would not be nipped in the bud, as Murphy predicts, as
there are countless underground betting organizations currently in
operation, and proto-AP would arguably be even more secure from law
enforcement, by benefit of its exclusive existence on the internet
with solid encryption and no face to face contact among users. Even at
the intermediate semi-morbid phases its possible proto-AP would not
garner significant government attention. Look at this
&lt;a href="http://www.stiffs.com/"&gt;http://www.stiffs.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly harmless, but the fact it has garnered no legal complaints is
a good indicator that real-AP would be able to go on the offensive for
some time before the Feds figured out where the threat is coming from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also still think the best idea is to design an autonomous system
with no publicly identified administrators even in the proto phase,
whether this will become feasible with future developments in
cryptography remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if AP did not go to the trouble of gradually building a customer
base, does not necessarily mean it will fail. Examine the case of
online gambling. Here we have people putting there money on games
where the "house" can completely manipulate the odds in its own favor
simply by changing a few lines of code, and the user will never know
unless he takes detailed notes on winning percentages. They do not
even have a reputation at stake like a traditional Las Vegas casino,
which could do the same with its electronic slot machines. If a Vegas
outfit says its slots pay out 99% or something, people who have no
good reason to trust that, still play by the thousands. Many people
are unaware that the Nevada Gaming Commission even exists, and
virtually none have any idea how good a job they do at enforcing
gambling regulations. And inexplicably they play online versions of
these same dubious games too, where they have far less control, and
nowhere near the trust of a "reputable" brick and mortar casino.
Online gambling rakes in millions, despite obvious security holes and
opportunities for abuse. An indicator that even if AP is not fool
proof as far as protecting bettor’s money from the admins, people will
still donate and predict. Maybe they’re just stupid, and maybe the
online casinos are actually honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Murphy also points out that if politicians resort to holding Congress
inside a NORAD bunker, then any information about deaths inside the
mountain can be easily manipulated by the government, thus disrupting
the rewarding of correct guessers. I doubt this will be an effective
countermeasure against AP. If the outside world never knows that the
Feds are lying about death dates, then potential assassins would not
be aware their successful hits might be in vain. They would then still
have motivation to mount their attacks, and only afterwards realize
the government’s press corps has cheated them out of their prize.
However, the people donating money have still gotten what they want: a
dead politician, and thus will continue donating. Since the assassin
will presumably either be dead, captured or in hiding, he will not be
able to warn anyone that the government is using information warfare
against AP. Thus the system continues as planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if it becomes common knowledge that the government
is not a reliable source of information, then it will be up to the
assassin to make the real death date known. Perhaps acquiring a tissue
sample from the victim and anonymously forwarding to independent
media, or videotaping the kill shot with some kind of provable date
stamp. This means the assassin has to take extra risk in getting close
enough to the body to grab some proof, or accidentally providing
incriminating evidence on tape, and also risk further exposure in
contacting the media. If the AP server is run autonomously, it will
have to be programmed to take into account the relative
trustworthiness of misinforming government sources versus potentially
nutcase indy media, and then make a decision as to the actual date of
death. If the information is too ambiguous, then it might extend prize
percentages to predictions on neighboring days, based on the
probability of being correct. In light of this possibility the
assassin would be smart to take out high interest loans and dump his
entire net worth into bets on days all around the planned kill date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of this development the assassin will have to take more risks
and thus insist on a higher prize before taking his chances. Thus this
government strategy will only serve to increase the equilibrium price
of assassinations, just like their moving into the bunker itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with applying a Bell curve distribution (different Bell!) to
the payoff percentages of the assassination market is insurance. In a
non-lethal prediction market, say for example a market to predict who
will win the next U.S. Presidential election, a form of economic
insurance would be the following strategy: A bettor believes that, if
Mr. Puppet is elected, the economy will fall. So this bettor places
their money on Mr. Puppet being elected, that way, if he is, and the
economy falls, the bettor is compensated financially by winning part of
the betting pool. In the same way, if a Bell curve is implemented to the
assassination market, more people who believe the economy will be worse
off without the assassinated leader will be driven to bet as a form of
insurance. Except, now that I think about it, this isn't really a
problem, as it would only increase the effective potential of the
assassination market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe I've completely diverted from Gametheoryland and inadvertently
strayed to close to the borders of Ancapland. If anyone has further
applications of game theory to assassination markets, or prediction
markets in general, please comment. Or, in anyone has objections or
correction, please comment as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/game-a-market.png" title="Game Theory Analysis of Tor &amp;quot;Assassination Market&amp;quot;" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/game-a-market.png&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>anarchism and Magic...cards</title><link href="/anarchism-and-magiccards.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-05-26T03:26:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-05-26:anarchism-and-magiccards.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, there was a period in which I answered the query,
"What do you want to be when you grow up?" with "I want to write flavor
text or make illustrations for magic cards."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_2369.jpg" title="Anarchist" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_2369.jpg" title="Anarchist" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/IMG_2369.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>How To Firewall and Ban The Authorities</title><link href="/how-to-firewall-and-ban-the-authorities.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-03-14T13:46:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-03-14:how-to-firewall-and-ban-the-authorities.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The folks at &lt;a href="http://www.telecomix.org/"&gt;Telecomix&lt;/a&gt; Crypto Munitions Bureau have put up a list of
&lt;a href="http://cryptoanarchy.org/wiki/Authority_Netblock_Blacklist"&gt;IP addresses of worldwide governments&lt;/a&gt; and agencies, so that you can
block them through your firewall. If you're running a server or a
domain, you can also modify the .htaccess file to ban these IPs from
accessing your site. You can also force anyone from the above listed IP
addresses, when attempting to connect to your site, to view a static
image instead. I would recommend something which clearly states why they
are not allowed access, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/toBeGoverned1.jpg" title="toBeGoverned" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details on how to do this modification, and nearly every other
conceivable modification of the .htaccess file, can be found &lt;a href="http://perishablepress.com/press/2006/01/10/stupid-htaccess-tricks/#sec7b"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, jeepers. This makes me so happy. So. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​(A) &amp;amp; \&amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/toBeGoverned1.jpg" title="toBeGoverned" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/toBeGoverned1.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Graceless: A Journal of the Radical Gothic</title><link href="/graceless-a-journal-of-the-radical-gothic.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-03-10T02:17:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-03-10:graceless-a-journal-of-the-radical-gothic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/graceless1-cover-240x300.jpg" title="graceless1-cover-240x300" /&gt;][]I'm very proud (and very late, due to security issues) to
announce that the first issue of &lt;a href="http://www.graceless.info/"&gt;Graceless&lt;/a&gt; has been released. We are
an international collective producing a printed and online journal of
the radical gothic. Printed copies are available &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Graceless-Journal-Radical-Gothic-1/dp/1456541145/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or if you
know me IRL you can just ask me for a copy on the cheap. Or, as cheap as
it gets, you can download the online version &lt;a href="http://www.graceless.info/pdfs/graceless1-web.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Also, I will be
tabling copies at the 2011 &lt;a href="https://sfbookfair.wordpress.com/"&gt;San Francisco Anarchist Bookfair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/graceless1-cover-240x300.jpg" title="graceless1-cover-240x300" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/graceless1-cover-240x300.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Anarchism"></category><category term="anarchist bookfair"></category><category term="gothic"></category><category term="graceless"></category><category term="radicalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Game Theory &amp; anarchism: Why Snitches Are Snitches, and Why Anarchists Are Not Snitches</title><link href="/game-theory-anarchism-why-snitches-are-snitches-and-why-anarchists-are-not-snitches.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-07T17:08:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-01-07:game-theory-anarchism-why-snitches-are-snitches-and-why-anarchists-are-not-snitches.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Consider the following logical game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Two suspects are arrested by the police. The police have insufficient
evidence for a conviction, and, having separated the prisoners, visit
each of them to offer the same deal. If one testifies for the
prosecution against the other (&lt;em&gt;defects&lt;/em&gt;) and the other remains silent
(&lt;em&gt;cooperates&lt;/em&gt;), the defector goes free and the silent accomplice
receives the full 10-year sentence. If both remain silent, both
prisoners are sentenced to only six months in jail for a minor charge.
If each betrays the other, each receives a four-year sentence. Each
prisoner must choose to betray the other or to remain silent. Each one
is assured that the other would not know about the betrayal before the
end of the investigation. How should the prisoners act?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the rational choice is not to snitch, and cross your fingers
that your accomplice does the same, right? Well, rationally thinking,
wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If each suspect only cares about minimizing their own jail time, then
the prisoner's dilemma forms a non-zero-sum game. (A zero-sum game is
one in which the total benefits and total losses of all players equal
zero, for instance, if Asimov, Bradbury, and Clarke dumpster a block of
tofu and Bradbury takes a larger piece, the others get less, but the
total benefits and losses is zero. A non-zero-sum game is one in which
the aggregate total gains and losses is not zero, meaning that everyone
will either collectively benefit or collectively suffer together.) In
game theory, the sole concern of each player is maximizing their own
payoff (less jail time), with no concern for the other player's payoff.
The curious Nash equilibrium (i.e. rationalized solution) for this game
is a Pareto-suboptimal solution, that is, rational choice dictates both
players to play &lt;em&gt;defect&lt;/em&gt;, even though each player's individual reward
would be greater if they both played cooperatively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Prisoners_dilemma_chart.png" title="Prisoner's_dilemma_chart" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As can be seen, each player faces the same choice: 1) 6 months/10 years,
or (2) no time/4 years. Clearly, the second choice is better. Which is
to say that snitching is better. Which doesn't exactly correspond to
actual human behaviour: snitching is the unfortunate exception, not the
rule. It just doesn't sit right at all, mathematically, statistically,
rationally, logically, or otherwise. But then, this is where things get
superrational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Douglas Hofstadter, in &lt;em&gt;Metamagical Themas&lt;/em&gt;, proposes that the
conception of rationality that leads “rational” players to defect is
faulty. Instead, Hofstadter posits an alternative rational behaviour,
which he terms “superrational”. Superrational thinking logically leads
to cooperation as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Superrational strategy is identical for both players, since both
    players are no longer playing for purely their own benefit, but for
    the benefit of minimizing jail time overall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, since both players will do exactly the same thing, the
    result lies on the diagonal of the payoff matrix. (Either both will
    defect or both will cooperate.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To minimize jail time from solutions on the diagonal, both players
    cooperate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superrational players behave in the following manner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a superrational player is playing against a known rational
    opponent, they will defect because this minimizes jail time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A superrational player only cooperates with other superrational
    players, whose thinking is correlated with theirs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a superrational players is playing against another player of
    unknown superrationality, the superrational player will either
    cooperate or defect based on the probability of the another player's
    superrationality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is therefore possible to cultivate a group morality which states that
foregoing minimized jail time for oneself in lieu of minimized jail time
overall is the appropriate behaviour. This is the most rational
behaviour, however it is only the most rational so long as the group
morality is maintained. Anarchist and politically radical groups often
support this group morality, and it is essential for all individuals
within these groups to uphold it in order for it to work correctly.
Therefore, snitches, who do not think superrationally, can be considered
as rational opponent players, which is terms for expulsion from the
group (i.e. the true superrational player, or radical, should snitch on
snitches, based on the logical rules outlined above, thus minimizing
jail time.) Even more reason for building trust and a sense of community
among politically radical groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Prisoners_dilemma_chart.png" title="Prisoner's_dilemma_chart" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Prisoners_dilemma_chart.png&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Fascism and the Occult II: The Future of Eugenics</title><link href="/fascism-and-the-occult-ii-the-future-of-eugenics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-12-09T18:58:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2010-12-09:fascism-and-the-occult-ii-the-future-of-eugenics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my continuing research on fascism within the occult, I have come
across a very well-written treatise advocating such views. The Order of
Nine Angles' &lt;em&gt;Book of Wyrd&lt;/em&gt;, a zine-sized manuscript outlining rituals,
runes, eugenics, and aeonics, with literary expositions on Nietzsche's
&lt;em&gt;Anti-Christ&lt;/em&gt; and the Old Norse &lt;em&gt;Poetic Edda&lt;/em&gt;, outlines the philosophy
and methods of what transhumanists sometimes term provolution: the
intentional, or pro-active, application of evolution upon a species.
“Man need not be a passive spectator or a victim of the 'gods' or 'fate'
but by understanding the laws of nature and the cosmos can, through his
Will, be an active agent in the evolutionary process.”^1^ states the
seventh point in their “Articles of Faith”. Within their doctrine of
cosmology, the universe is cyclic – a continual oscillation between
creative and destructive principles yields dialectical historical
stages, the study of which is called aeonics. In this process of
renewal, Nietzsche's Übermensch is seen as a spiritually individualistic
(i.e. satanic), space-faring transhuman, the next stage in the evolution
of humankind.[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Eugenics_congress_logo.png" title="Eugenics_congress_logo" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Book of Wyrd&lt;/em&gt;, aeonics and its implications for future human
cultural and biological manifestations are explained by a continuation
of the ideas proposed by German historian and philosopher Oswald
Spengler in &lt;em&gt;The Decline of the West&lt;/em&gt;: “...while Spengler predicts the
close of Western Civilization, [Stephen] Brown considers an option which
goes beyond it. Spengler describes Western Civilization as 'Faustian'.
Its symbol is limitless space. This is reflected in its exploration and
colonization, art, architecture (e.g. the Gothic spire), and a form of
science that seeks to unveil the secrets of nature. Its reach is
infinite. 'Faustian' is the 'race soul' of the West that makes it
unique. As we've seen, while Spengler points to the conclusion of
Western Civilization like others before it, Brown suggests what might
come after it if the opportunities are seized by those few who have a
sense of destiny. And what is this possible destiny? The logical outcome
of the Faustian will: Space Colonization. [...]Brown also points out the
potential this would have for cultural variation (and by implication
biological evolution). It would see the creation of a myriad of new,
self-contained cultural laboratories throughout space, and the expansion
of man's destiny to infinity. Should we grasp the opportunities to build
upon the ruins of the post-Western world, the destiny of mankind will be
to play amongst the stars.” ^2^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point to which I find this text and its doctrine interesting is its
similar relation to tenets of various individualist anarchisms. These
latter strive to emphasize the hegemony of the individual's Will over
the presiding external forces of collective groups, society, traditions,
and ideological systems. Individualist anarchism commonly rejects
romantic notions of revolution, which would require social organization
to produce alternative systems, instead it often favors more
evolutionary methods of social experimentation and education. Thus,
fascism and anarchism can be seen to differ only in their means of
producing a new society, not in that end thereof. That is to say,
individualist anarchism and fascism both favor immediate methods of
integrating the new society into the old one, resulting in the
evolutionary displacement and eventual extinction of those who remain
unable to adapt; the only divergence between the two ideologies is that
anarchism retains romantic notions of a return to a fantasized
state-of-nature, whereby improperly fitted individuals are culled by
“natural” processes, and fascism often supports the “ethical necessity”
of eugenics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In The Order of Nine Angles doctrine, eugenics is seen as a necessary
destructive principle emanating from the principles of aeonics. From an
ecological standpoint, humankind's speciesism and ecocidical disregard
for biosystems (which, in turn, degrade human quality of life through
rising occurrence of ecological disasters, and pollution, among other
factors) can be regarded as a form of deliberate eugenics already in
practice. It is unnecessary to recount here the numerous reasons why the
term eugenics has negative connotations, what is more pertinent is an
emerging requisite application of ethical philosophy to positive
eugenics, or transhumanist provolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ancient Greek ethical philosophy, there was the concept of
&lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;, literally “good spirited,” the ways in which humans should
conduct themselves in order to live happier lives and secure a better
world for future generations. Eudaimonia is often connected to the term
&lt;em&gt;arete&lt;/em&gt;, or virtue. Virtue, here, does not carry the weighty and
puritanical Christian connotations of charity, patience, and
uprightness, since it also includes many non-moral individual objectives
such as good health and beauty. It is, in fact, quite similar to the
occult concept of Will. Stoic philosophy is ripe with eudaimonism:
Cleanthes of Assos explained it as “living in agreement with nature”,
while Chrysippus believed it was “living in accordance with experience
of what happens by nature.” ^3^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As future eugenics, concerning the emerging technologies in
nanotechnology, neurobiology, information technology, genetics, and
cognitive science, is no longer a negative practice, that is to say, it
is not concerned with taking away, culling, or cleaning the gene pool,
but with adding to potentialities of individual enhancement, its
corresponding ethics is no longer negative. It becomes a question of
&lt;em&gt;what one should not do&lt;/em&gt;, rather than the historical imposing
regulations of authoritarian eugenics pertaining to what one &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;
do. “[I]f...[the] methods [of genetic engineering] allow children to be
produced with a higher intellectual level, in a democratic state, this
will generate a new eugenic wave. This time, however, the task will be
to help people with a low intellectual coefficient to raise this
coefficient (the task of positive eugenics) in themselves and in their
children rather than to prevent the appearance of children in such
people (the task of negative eugenics).” ^4^As modern thought becomes
increasingly non-dichotomous, the black-and-white of the weary old
nature-versus-nurture argument fades to voluminous greys. Collimately,
humans can no longer rely on a transparent definition of what is
“natural” to define them. Most of us were not raised by wolves in the
Ukraine; we are already the products of positive eugenic systems such as
education and language. The modern human is already an “unnatural”
creature. Environmental philosopher Mark Sagoff argues that the problem
of engineering the human genome “is not so much that it will alienate or
separate us from our human nature – from what is given or contingent –
but that it will increasingly make us responsible for it”. ^5^&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full Text of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/ONA-The-Black-Order-Book-of-Wyrd.pdf"&gt;ONA (The Black Order) - Book of Wyrd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Works Cited&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 The Black Order. &lt;em&gt;The Book of Wyrd&lt;/em&gt;. Unknown: Realist Publications,
1993. p. 3. Print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 ibid. p. 15&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 Dirk Baltzly (Feb 7, 2008). &lt;a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/stoicism/"&gt;"Stoicism"&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Stanford Encyclopedia of
Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/stoicism/"&gt;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/stoicism/&lt;/a&gt;.
Retrieved 2010-12-05. "But what is happiness? The Epicureans' answer was
deceptively straightforward: the happy life is the one which is most
pleasant. (But their account of what the highest pleasure consists in
was not at all straightforward.) Zeno's answer was "a good flow of life"
(Arius Didymus, 63A) or "living in agreement," and Cleanthes clarified
that with the formulation that the end was "living in agreement with
nature" (Arius Didymus, 63B). Chrysippus amplified this to (among other
formulations) "living in accordance with experience of what happens by
nature;" later Stoics inadvisably, in response to Academic attacks,
substituted such formulations as "the rational selection of the primary
things according to nature." The Stoics' specification of what happiness
consists in cannot be adequately understood apart from their views about
value and human psychology."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 Yudin, B. G. "The Creation of a Transhuman." &lt;em&gt;Herald of the Russian
Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 77.3 (2007): 247-53. Web. 8 Dec 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 Sagoff, Mark. “Nature and Human Nature”. &lt;em&gt;Is Human Nature Obsolete?:
Genetics, Bioengineering, and the Future of the Human Condition&lt;/em&gt;.
Boston, MIT Press, 2005. pp. 89-90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Eugenics_congress_logo.png" title="Eugenics_congress_logo" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Eugenics_congress_logo.png&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="aeonics"></category><category term="Ancient Greek philosophy"></category><category term="environmentalism"></category><category term="eugenics"></category><category term="fascism"></category><category term="individualist anarchism"></category><category term="morality"></category><category term="Nietzsche"></category><category term="occult"></category><category term="Oswald Spengler"></category><category term="provolution"></category><category term="state-of-nature"></category><category term="Stephen Brown"></category><category term="transhumanism"></category></entry><entry><title>Alchemical Bust Card</title><link href="/alchemical-bust-card.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-03-10T14:07:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2010-03-10:alchemical-bust-card.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/Alchemical-bust-card.jpg" title="Alchemical bust card" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/Alchemical-bust-card.jpg" title="Alchemical bust card" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/Alchemical-bust-card.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>