<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Pelican Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/physics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2011-07-28T20:17:00Z</updated><entry><title>Post-Rev Theoretical Physics</title><link href="/post-rev-theoretical-physics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-07-28T20:17:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-07-28:post-rev-theoretical-physics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently asked by two separate, presumably non-anarchist, entities
if and how theoretical or high-energy physics would exist in an
anarchist society. There are several implicit underlying questions in
this basic question, and I will attempt to answer each in turn. I have
been asked this question by other anarchists before, and my usual
response is that nothing would change in my personal situation. I work
odd jobs, find strange ways to pay for things when needed, garden and
sometimes forage for food, and try to never spend money,  so that I can
devote most of my time to research. While I believe that what I and
other physicists are doing is for the ultimate good of humanity --
trying to understand the seemingly chaotic patterns of our universe,
which is fundamental to any correct understanding of anything else --
we're not exactly putting food in hungry mouths, ensuring shelters for
the houseless, providing medical aid to the sick and old, or doing any
of the number of things which are generally considered socially
beneficial. As an anarchist, I do not believe it is society's
responsibility to support me in my research unless my research is
directly assisting others in need. To believe contrary would be entirely
selfish, not to mention entirely ignorant of context: the context here
being that, while, yes, I am a unique individual with my own sets of
needs and desires (namely, to sit around staring at sheets of equations
all day, with a break to mix a heaping of vegan gluten-free protein
powder into a glass of water), &lt;em&gt;there is no such thing as a system in
total isolation&lt;/em&gt;. Individualist anarchist as I may be, if I have learned
anything from physics I know that one for a fact. Thus, I must take into
account that if I am not contributing to the rest of society, then the
rest of society owes nothing to me. And as much as I would like to
discount the rest of human society, I still have to share air and soil
and a few other things with them while I'm stuck on this stupid cosmic
shitpile. Anyway, what this all boils down to is that there is very
little opportunity for a physicist to only work on physics in an
anarchist society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this time the question is different. Non-anarchists have begun to
ask the question, and now the answer must take a different form. As I
mentioned, it entails other implicit underlying questions: What will the
anarchist revolution look like? Will it be a series of bloody and
dramatic confrontations with authorities in the streets? Will it be a
gradualist or reformist shift in sociocultural perspectives? Will it be
a total collapse of modern civilization and requisite technologies? Will
"rogue" AIs or the emergence of trans-/post- humans enable us to
cooperate efficiently &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt; without ingrained hierarchies? Will
someone finally hack the gibson and ';shutdown --? What will the nascent
anarchist society look like, and what type of economic system will it
implement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So best case scenario, in my opinion, is that most of the 6.775 x 10^9^
humans on this planet aren't killed, maimed, wounded, incapacitated,
starved, or in any other way made incapable of functioning. Being a
theoretical physicist...well, let's just say we're a little bit of a
niche. We're highly specialized, and we require data from experimental
physicists to assist the creation and prove the validity of our claims,
which requires even more specialization and fancy equipment, and when
things get that fancy and specialized it requires a much larger societal
support structure. So, for utilitarian purposes, I don't want everybody
dead. Also, and this is a point of controversy among anarchists,
economics: it's a problem. My friends who are proponents of gift
economics somehow think that post-(A)-revolution is going to be magical
happy anarcholand where everybody's transformed into sparkly rainbow
sharebears. I will not place myself within the diaphanous caricature so
often drafted for Kropotkin and Godwin, that humans are essentially kind
and selfless creatures. I think that game theory shows us the
possibility of a fully functional anarchist society, and it even shows
us that this is the most rational and rewarding scenario; however, this
assumes that all players are predominantly rational, which is not the
case. Some of us may be noble, kind, and good-hearted creatures, and
most of us have fleeting moments of nobility, but for many humans the
prime motivation is selfishness and greed. That is not to say that this
is of necessity the case, nor that they cannot be taught otherwise, but
in the meantime I see no problems with taking advantage of baser desires
in the less noble members of the human species and redirecting their
motivation for the common good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having a conversation with my friend Will, who is also a
theoretical physicist, I've decided to somewhat revise my statements.
Will pointed out that everyone is rational, it's just that their
operational and observational contexts are limited. Which, in my
opinion, is no excuse. It's laziness. It's a lack of vigilance. If you
can't go out and seek broader context than that which is handed to you,
then you're lazy. And thus, still ignoble. And I'm getting off track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So physics after the anarchist revolution. My guess is that not much
will change, unless the primmies are actually the apocalyptic harbingers
of doom which they romanticize themselves as. People tend to work best
in small cells, and many bleeding edge tech research firms tend to
follow this model. Even larger companies, e.g. Google, are actually a
conglomeration of small cells. The difference would be the person at the
top, cutting themself a 7+ digit paycheck, just for "owning" the rest of
the company. That probably isn't going to stick around. In fact, I would
argue, for it to truly be an anarchist society, that person can't stick
around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably skipped a few things in my explanation. I guess I just mean
to say that technological and theoretical development will be faster and
more effective in a free society, and also that not as much will change
as some might think, given my version of the revolution. Feel free to
ask more question if you feel I haven't thought things through, or
glossed over points.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="anarchist societies"></category><category term="apocalypse"></category><category term="emerging technologies"></category><category term="future"></category><category term="mutual cooperation"></category><category term="opinion"></category><category term="physics"></category><category term="Post-Civ"></category><category term="post-revolution"></category><category term="theoretical physics"></category></entry><entry><title>Cosmology</title><link href="/cosmology.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-07T04:02:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-06-07:cosmology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've taken to running half marathons while reading theoretical physics
textbooks and listening to industrial or black metal. It's the best way
I've found so far to murderdeadkill social anxiety and panic attacks,
not to mention it feels hella badass. One of my dearest friends is the
only member of &lt;a href="http://www.nomadicwarmachine.net/"&gt;the only anarchist industrial project&lt;/a&gt;, so far as I
know. One of the songs on their album (which, of course, can be
&lt;a href="http://www.nomadicwarmachine.net/mp3s/ihaveagun.zip"&gt;downloaded for free&lt;/a&gt;), "Aspect of Illa", starts with a quote from the
movie &lt;em&gt;Ninja Assassin&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;"Oy, here's a question for ya.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Which one o' these words don't belong:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Laptop, space shuttle, nanotechnology, ninja."&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is totally a trick question, because &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; all four word go
together perfectly fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a scan of the textbook I'm reading, because it wasn't already up
online. Er, well, it apparently was, but the site got a takedown notice.
I hope they get a kick out of trying to stick their takedown notice in
the mailbox of a burned down house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Springer Tracts in Modern Physics 210: Cosmology (click for .pdfs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Front-Cover.pdf"&gt;Front Cover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/00-Preface-ToC-and-Notations.pdf"&gt;00 - Preface, ToC, and Notations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/01-Chapter-1-Basics.pdf"&gt;01 - Chapter 1 - Basics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/02-Chapter-2-Relativity.pdf"&gt;02 - Chapter 2 - Relativity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/03-Chapter-3-Expansion.pdf"&gt;03 - Chapter 3 - Expansion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/04-Chapter-4-Cosmometry.pdf"&gt;04 - Chapter 4 - Cosmometry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/05-Chapter-5-Matter-and-Radiation.pdf"&gt;05 - Chapter 5 - Matter and Radiation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/06-Chapter-6-Standard-Synthesis.pdf"&gt;06 - Chapter 6 - Standard Synthesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/07-Chapter-7-Inflation.pdf"&gt;07 - Chapter 7 - Inflation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/08-Chapter-8-Structure-Formation-in-the-Opaque-Universe.pdf"&gt;08 - Chapter 8 - Structure Formation in the Opaque Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/09-Chapter-9-Structure-Formation-in-the-Transparent-Universe.pdf"&gt;09 - Chapter 9 - Structure Formation in the Transparent Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/10-Chapter-10-Higher-Dimensions.pdf"&gt;10 - Chapter 10 - Higher Dimensions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/11-Chapter-11-Topological-Quasi-Particles.pdf"&gt;11 - Chapter 11 - Topological Quasi-Particles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/12-Chapter-12-Quantum-Cosmology.pdf"&gt;12 - Chapter 12 - Quantum Cosmology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/13-Chapter-13-Machian-Aspects.pdf"&gt;13 - Chapter 13 - Machian Aspects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/14-Chapter-14-Anthropic-Aspects.pdf"&gt;14 - Chapter 14 - Anthropic Aspects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/15-Index.pdf"&gt;15 - Index&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Back-Cover.pdf"&gt;Back Cover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this book, I now 80% believe in macroevolution and primordial
nucleosynthesis (&lt;em&gt;gasp&lt;/em&gt;, I know. Don't freak out, I was agnostic on the
matter until I could gather more information.) And chemistry makes
complete sense now. I've asked every chemist I've ever met to explain
their subject at the particle level, and all have failed miserably,
blank stares abound. I was so sure that elements should be able to
mutate  into other elements, they're all made of the same sub-atomic
particles after all. Turns out, not only was my thinking correct, but
there are 3D diagrams detailing precisely how this transmogrification
occurs. (Chapter 6, Fig. 6.10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I take issue with the use of the Einstein-deSitter universal model
for calculating the reentry time from the inflationary period in
cosmological evolution. (Chapter 8, Eqs. 8.9 - 8.13) According to the
book, this makes the calculations "only four orders of magnitude greater
than they should be". Apparently, this is some sort of improvement.
Well, I take issue. Instead of defining inflationary perturbations
according to the curvature parameter of the Einstein-deSitter universe,
which is supposed to be used to describe cold matter only, shouldn't we
be using the Friedmann-Lemaître model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I probably just lost everyone, I'm going to blather on about
something more trivial: &lt;a href="http://www.metal-archives.com/reviews/Darkspace/Dark_Space_III/192246/"&gt;Darkspace&lt;/a&gt;. Is a black metal group exploring
concepts in theoretical physics. Also good listening while
reading/running. One of their songs, &lt;em&gt;3.11&lt;/em&gt; (all their songs and albums
are numbered, not titled), has a quote from John Carpenter's film
&lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Prince_of_Darkness_%28film%29"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prince of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which might take the cake for second corniest
geek movie ever, right beneath Hackers. The quote comes from a portion
of the film where the main characters have been possessed by a neon
green sentient goop, which is Satan himself, and are theorizing satanic
metaphysical interpretations of particle physics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;"Suppose what your faith has said&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;is essentially correct.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Suppose there is a universal mind&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;controlling everything,&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;a god willing the behaviour&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;of every subatomic particle.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Well, every particle has an anti-particle,&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;its mirror image, its negative side.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this universal mind resides&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;in the mirror image instead of in our universe&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;as we wanted to believe.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe he's anti-god,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;bringing darkness instead of light."&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrong. Wrong on so many levels that I'm positively delighted. And, now
that I have ensured that the other physicists won't take me seriously,
and the other anarchists won't follow a word I'm saying, I'm going
running.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="anarchist industrial music"></category><category term="black metal"></category><category term="cosmology"></category><category term="dark matter"></category><category term="darkspace"></category><category term="mach's holographic principle"></category><category term="macroevolution"></category><category term="nomadic war machine"></category><category term="primordial nucleosynthesis"></category><category term="prince of darkness"></category><category term="quantum cosmology"></category><category term="Satanism"></category><category term="social anxiety"></category><category term="springer tracts in modern physics"></category><category term="string theory"></category><category term="theoretical physics"></category></entry><entry><title>Interactive Schrödinger's Cat</title><link href="/interactive-schrodingers-cat.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-03T18:33:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-06-03:interactive-schrodingers-cat.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.phobe.com/s_cat/s_cat.html"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is kind of cute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal interpretation of &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Schrödinger_equation"&gt;Schrödinger's equations&lt;/a&gt; would
traditionally be to deny the actuality of wave function collapse, which
is part of the &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Many_worlds_interpretation"&gt;Many-Worlds Interpretation&lt;/a&gt; of quantum mechanics, but
I haven't looked into this or really considered it since I was fourteen
(&lt;em&gt;thousand&lt;/em&gt;) years old. I thought it was awesome at the time because
philosophically it meant that there exists a universe in which all
societies operate anarchistically, and if I just invented a proper time
machine I could chrono-emigrate there. I figured building a time machine
&lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to be simpler than fixing all the problems we have here and now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: &lt;a href="http://redshift.vif.com/JournalFiles/V13NO4PDF/V13N4OST.pdf"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is interesting too. It explains why coordinate
transformations in Schrödinger groups are dissimilar to those of
Galilean or Poincaré groups, because phase shifts under Lorentz boosts
are variant and dependent upon the mass(es) of the particle(s). Thus, in
order for the boosts to become covariant, proper time and relativity of
simultaneity need to be taken into account and prove central to even
non-relativistic quantum mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="app"></category><category term="quantum physics"></category><category term="schodinger's cat"></category></entry><entry><title>Chlorosis!</title><link href="/chlorosis.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-20T14:49:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-04-20:chlorosis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_548" align="alignleft" width="225"
caption="Albino Redwood foliage"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Albino_redwood-225x300.jpg" title="Albino_redwood" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh sweet void. I spent some of my traveling time a few months ago
hunting the elusive albino redwood trees in northern California. Those
trees have a genetic mutation which prevents them from producing
chlorophyll, and so they survive by parasitism, attaching themselves to
the root system of a nearby tree to leech nutrients. Those trees are
absolutely breathtaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this morning I go to water the sprouts for my garden, and I find that
one of my Bok Choi sprouts lacks any chlorophyll! Eeks! So cute! So
rare! Genetic mutations! So! Cute!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't done any genetic testing yet, so this could be simply an
extreme case of chlorosis instead of an actual mutation. Plants like
this don't normally live very long, but I'm going to try to keep this
little guy alive and happy as long as possible to figure out what's
going on here.[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/IMG_2316-225x300.jpg" title="bok choi chlorosis" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other questions which have been raised include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​1) Why am I attracted to genetic mutations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​2) Would the most ethical action be a mercy killing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​3) What is the nutritional value of a plant with severe chlorosis? Is
it like eating pickles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​4) How do I make more of these? Is it possible to clone things at home
yet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​5) What are the odds of this condition occuring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/IMG_2310-300x225.jpg" title="bok choi chlorosis 2" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Albino_redwood-225x300.jpg" title="Albino_redwood" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Albino_redwood.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/IMG_2316-225x300.jpg" title="bok choi chlorosis" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/IMG_2316.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/IMG_2310-300x225.jpg" title="bok choi chlorosis 2" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/IMG_2310.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="albinism"></category><category term="albino sequoia sempervirens"></category><category term="bok choi"></category><category term="chlorosis"></category><category term="genetic mutations"></category><category term="new friend"></category><category term="parasitism"></category><category term="redwoods"></category></entry><entry><title>Unparticle Physics</title><link href="/unparticle-physics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-07T18:36:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-04-07:unparticle-physics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently discovered a young branch of theoretical physics: unparticle
physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brief and simple explanation of the theory of unparticles from the
Wikipedia entry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Elementary_particle" title="Elementary particle"&gt;particles&lt;/a&gt; exist in states that may be characterized by a
certain &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Energy"&gt;energy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Momentum"&gt;momentum&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Mass"&gt;mass&lt;/a&gt;. In most of the
&lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Standard_Model"&gt;Standard Model&lt;/a&gt; of particle physics, particles of the same type
cannot exist in another state with all these properties scaled up or
down by a common factor – &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Electron" title="Electron"&gt;electrons&lt;/a&gt;, for example, always have the
same mass regardless of their energy or momentum. But this is not
always the case: massless particles, such as &lt;a href="https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Photon" title="Photon"&gt;photons&lt;/a&gt;, can exist
with their properties scaled equally. This immunity to scaling is
called "scale invariance".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of unparticles comes from conjecturing that there may be
"stuff" that does not necessarily have zero mass but is still
scale-invariant, with the same physics regardless of a change of
length (or equivalently energy). This stuff is unlike particles, and
described as unparticle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such unparticle stuff has not been observed, which suggests that if it
exists, it must couple with normal matter weakly at observable
energies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_531" align="alignleft" width="335"
caption="Power Spectrum for Hawking Radiation of
Unparticles"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Hawking-radiation-of-unparticles.png" title="Hawking radiation of unparticles" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been reading up on this theory and wanted to post some academic
papers so that others may do the same. However, I am having one
difficulty: I have no knowledge of Banks-Zaks fields, and Unparticle
Physics is almost entirely based upon them. My university doesn't have a
subscription to the journal for that year, and I can't get the paper
without paying \$31.50. Now, I don't mean to whine or sound like a
cheapskate, but I eat mostly rice and boiled cabbage, so \$31.50 could
feed me for like two weeks. Plus, who ever heard of theoretical
physicists demanding monetary compensation for their ideas, and not
uploading their articles to arXiv? Crazy IP nazis. The paper I need is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;"Perturbative-variational calculations of ground-state energies of lattice gauge theories"&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by T. Banks and A Zaks, and it was published in 1982 in Nuclear Physics
B. If anyone has this paper, could you please send it my way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's all the other papers I have collected thus far: (click for .pdfs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Unparticle-Physics.pdf"&gt;Unparticle Physics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Another-Odd-Thing-About-Unparticle-Physics.pdf"&gt;Another Odd Thing About Unparticle Physics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Unparticle-Self-Interactions.pdf"&gt;Unparticle Self-Interactions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Uncosmology.pdf"&gt;Uncosmology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Cosmology-with-Unparticles.pdf"&gt;Cosmology with Unparticles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Unparticle-Dark-Energy.pdf"&gt;Unparticle Dark Energy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Hawking-Radiation-of-Unparticles.pdf"&gt;Hawking Radiation of Unparticles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Hawking-radiation-of-unparticles.png" title="Hawking radiation of unparticles" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/Hawking-radiation-of-unparticles.png&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="banks-zaks fields"></category><category term="beyond the standard model"></category><category term="black holes"></category><category term="dark matter/energy"></category><category term="fuck IP!"></category><category term="hawking radiation"></category><category term="theoretical physics"></category><category term="uncosmology"></category><category term="unparticle physics"></category></entry><entry><title>Famous Physicists on Mysticism #3: "Science and the Beautiful" by Werner Heisenberg</title><link href="/famous-physicists-on-mysticism-3-science-and-the-beautiful-by-werner-heisenberg.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-09T19:28:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2011-01-09:famous-physicists-on-mysticism-3-science-and-the-beautiful-by-werner-heisenberg.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Ohioan-Native-Kin.jpg" title="Ohioan &amp;amp; Native Kin" /&gt;][]I would like to express again, for those who missed the first
two installments of this series, that the views expressed within the
essays are those of the physicists who wrote them, not me. It's called
"Famous Physicists on Mysticism," not "isis agora lovecruft on Mysticism."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This essay is one of my favourite, and it is partly the inspiration for
the title of this blog, although full credit has to go to Ryne Warner,
whom I lived with as a roommate for several years. He's an experimental
composer, and one of his projects is called &lt;a href="http://www.myspace.com/oryne"&gt;Ohioan&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/1-Patterns-in-the-Void.mp3"&gt;first
song&lt;/a&gt; off their album which was released last year is also the title
of this blog. If you're into Thee Silver Mt. Zion or any of the other
numerous sounds that came out the Montreal scene in the first half of
the last decade, you'll like Ohioan. I used to sneak into their practice
sessions just to stare at the fiddle player. His movements were a
physical counter-point to the melodies. I cried a little bit one of
those times, it was too pretty. I really hope he doesn't read
this...Just to show off Ryne's talent: I highly recommend listening to
&lt;a href="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/4-Some-Will-Live.mp3"&gt;Some Will Live&lt;/a&gt;. So. Damn. Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science and the Beautiful&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Werner Heisenberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it will be best if, without any initial attempt at a
philosophical analysis of the concept of “beauty,” we simply ask where
we can meet the beautiful in the sphere of exact science. Here I may
perhaps be allowed to begin with a personal experience. When, as a small
boy, I was attending the lowest classes of the Max-Gynasium here in
Munich, I became interested in numbers. It gave me pleasure to get to
know their properties, to find out, for example, whether they were prime
numbers or not, and to test whether they could perhaps be represented as
sums of squares, or eventually to prove that there must be infinitely
many primes. Now since my father thought my knowledge of Latin to be
much more important than my numerical interests, he brought home to me
one day from the National Library a treatise written in Latin by the
mathematician Leopold Kronecker, in which the properties of whole
numbers were set in relation to the geometrical problem of dividing a
circle into a number of equal parts. How my father happened to light on
this particular investigations from the middle of the last century I do
not know. But the study of Kronecker's work made a deep impression on
me. I sensed a quite immediate beauty in the fact that, from the problem
of partitioning a circle, whose simplest cases were, of course, familiar
to us in school, it was possible to learn something about the totally
different sort of questions involved in elementary number theory. Far in
the distance, no doubt, there already floated the question whether whole
numbers and geometrical forms exist, i.e., whether they are there
outside the human mind or whether they have merely been created by this
mind as instruments for understanding the world. But at that time I was
not yet able to think about such problems. The impression of something
very beautiful was, however, perfectly direct; it required no
justification or explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_428" align="alignleft" width="248"
caption="Werner Heisenberg"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Heisenberg.jpg" title="Heisenberg" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what was beautiful here? Even in antiquity there were two
definitions of beauty which stood in a certain opposition to one
another. The controversy between them play a great part, especially
during the Renaissance. The one describes beauty as the proper
conformity of the parts to one another, and to the whole. The other,
stemming from Plotinus, describes it, without any reference to parts, as
the translucence of the eternal splendor of the “one” through the
material phenomenon. In our mathematical example, we shall have to stop
short, initially, at the first definition. The parts here are the
properties of whole numbers and laws of geometrical constructions, while
the whole is obviously the underlying system of mathematical axioms to
which arithmetic and Euclidean geometry belong—the great structure of
interconnection guaranteed by the consistency of the axiom system. We
perceive that the individual parts fit together, that, as parts, they do
indeed belong to this whole, and, without any reflection, we feel the
completeness and simplicity of this axiom system to be beautiful. Beauty
is therefore involved with the age-old problem of the “one” and the
“many” which occupied—in close connection with the problem of “being”
and “becoming”—a central position in early Greek philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the roots of exact science are also to be found at this very
point, it will be as well to retrace in broad outline the currents of
thought in that early age. At the starting point of the Greek philosophy
of nature there stands the question of a basic principle, from which the
colorful variety of phenomena can be explained. However strangely it may
strike us, the well-known answer of Thales—”Water is the material first
principle of all things”—contains, according to Nietzsche, three basic
philosophical demands which were to become important in the developments
that followed: first, that one should seek for such a unitary basic
principle; second, that the answer should be given only rationally, that
is, not by reference to a myth; and third and finally, that in this
context the material aspect of the world must play a deciding role.
Behind these demands there stands, of course, the unspoken recognition
that understanding can never mean anything more than the perception of
connections, i.e., unitary features of marks of affinity in the
manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if such a unitary principle of all things exists, then—and this was
the next step along this line of thought—one is straightaway brought up
against the question how it can serve to account for the fact of change.
The difficulty is particularly apparent in the celebrated paradox of
Parmenides. Only being is; non-being is not. But if only being is, there
cannot be anything outside this being that articulates it or could
brings about changes. Hence being will have to be conceived as eternal,
uniform, and unlimited in space and time. The changes we experience can
thus only be an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greek thought could not stay with this paradox for very long. The
eternal flux of appearances was immediately given, and the problem was
to explain it. In attempting to overcome the difficulty, various
philosophers struck out in different directions. One road led to the
atomic theory of Democritus. In addition to being, non-being can still
exist as a possibility, namely as the possibility for movement and form,
or, in other words, as empty space. Being is repeatable, and thus we
arrive at the picture of atoms in the void—the picture that has since
become infinitely fruitful as a foundation for natural science. But of
this road we shall say no more just now. Our purpose, rather, is to
present in more detail the other road, which led to Plato's Ideas, and
which carried us directly into the problem of beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_429" align="alignright" width="246"
caption="Pythagoras"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/pythagoras1.jpg" title="Pythagoras" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This road begins in the school of Pythagoras. It is there that the
notion is said to have originated that mathematics, the mathematical
order, was the basic principle whereby the multiplicity of phenomena
could be accounted for. Of Pythagoras himself we know little. His
disciples seem, in fact, to have been a religious sect, and only the
doctrine of transmigration and the laying down of certain moral and
religious rules and prohibitions can be traces with any certainty to
Pythagoras. But among these disciples—and this was what mattered
subsequently—a preoccupation with music and mathematics played an
important role. Here it was that Pythagoras is said to have made the
famous discovery that vibrating strings under equal tension sound
together in harmony if their lengths are in a simple numerical ratio.
The mathematical structure, namely the numerical ratio as a source of
harmony, was certainly one of the most momentous discoveries in the
history of mankind. The harmonious concord of two strings yields a
beautiful sound. Owing to the discomfort caused by beat-effects, the
human ear find dissonance disturbing, but consonance, the peace of
harmony, it finds beautiful. Thus the mathematical relation was also the
source of beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beauty, so the first of our ancient definitions ran, in the proper
conformity of the parts to one another and to the whole. The parts here
are the individual notes, while the whole is the harmonious sound. The
mathematical relation can , therefore, assemble two initially
independent parts into a whole, and so produce beauty. This discovery
effected a breakthrough, in Pythagorean doctrine, to entirely new forms
of thought, and so brought it about that the ultimate basis of all being
was no longer envisaged as a sensory material—such as water, in
Thales—but as an ideal principle of form. This was to state a basic idea
which later provided the foundation for all exact science. Aristotle, in
his &lt;em&gt;Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt;, reports that the Pythagoreans, “...who were the first
to take up mathematics, not only advanced in this study, but also having
been brought up in it they thought its principles were the principles of
all things....Since, again, they saw that the modifications and the
ratios of the musical scales were expressible in numbers; since, then,
all other things seemed in their whole nature to be modelled on numbers;
and numbers seemed to be the first things in the whole of nature, they
supposed the elements of numbers to be the elements of all things, and
the whole heaven to be a musical scale and a number.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding of the colorful multiplicity of the phenomena was thus to
come about be recognizing in them unitary principles of form, which can
be expressed in the language of mathematics. By this, too a close
connection was established between the intelligible and the beautiful.
For if the beautiful is conceived as a conformity of the parts to one
another and to the whole, and if, on the other hand, all understanding
is first made possible by means of this formal connection, the
experience of connections either understood or at least, guessed at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_431" align="alignleft" width="288"
caption="Plato"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Plato_1_lg.gif" title="Plato" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step along this road was taken by Plato with the formulation of
his theory of Ideas. Plato contrasts the imperfect shapes of the
corporeal world of the senses with the perfect forms of mathematics; the
imperfectly circular orbits of the stars, say, with the perfection of
the mathematically defined circle. Material things are the copies, the
shadow images, of ideal shapes in reality; moreover, as we should be
tempted to continue nowadays, these ideal shapes are actual because
because and insofar as they become “act”-ive in material events. Plato
thus distinguishes here with complete clarity a corporeal being
accessible to the senses and a purely ideal being apprehensible not by
the senses but only through acts of the mind. Now is this ideal being in
any way in need of man's thought in order to be brought forth by him. On
the contrary, it is the true being, of which the corporeal world and
human thinking are mere reproductions. As their name already indicates,
the apprehension of Ideas by the human mind is more an artistic
intuiting, a half-conscious intimation, than a knowledge conveyed by the
understanding. It is a reminiscence of forms that were already implanted
in this soul before its existence on earth. The central Idea is that of
the Beautiful and the Good, in which the divine becomes visible and at
sight of which the wings of the soul begin to grow. A passage in the
&lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt; expresses the following thought: the soul is awe-stricken and
shudders at the sight of the beautiful, for it feels that something is
evoked in it that was not imparted to it from without by the senses but
has always been already laid down there in a deeply unconscious region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let us come back one more to understanding and thus, to natural
science. The colorful multiplicity of the phenomena can be understood,
according to Pythagoras and Plato, because and insofar as it is
underlain by unitary principles of form susceptible of mathematical
representation. This postulate already constitutes an anticipation of
the entire program of contemporary exact science. It could not, however,
be carried through in antiquity, since an empirical knowledge of the
details of natural processes was largely lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first attempt to penetrate into these details was undertaken, as we
know, in the philosophy of Aristotle. But in view of the infinite wealth
initially presented here to the observing student of nature and the
total lack of any sort of viewpoint from which an order might have been
discernible, the unitary principles of form sought by Pythagoras and
Plato were obliged to give place to the description of details. Thus
there arose the conflict that has continued to this day in the debates,
for example, between experimental and theoretical physics; the conflict
between the empiricist, who by careful and scrupulous detailed
investigation first furnishes the presuppositions for an understanding
of nature, and the theoretician, who creates mathematical pictures
whereby he seeks to order and so to understand nature—mathematical
pictures that prove themselves, not only by their correct depiction of
experience, but also and more especially by their simplicity and beauty,
to be the true Ideas underlying the course of nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle, as an empiricist, was critical of the Pythagoreans, who, he
said, “are not seeking for theories and causes to account for observed
facts, but rather forcing their observations and trying to accommodate
them to certain theories and opinions of their own” and were thus
setting up, one might say, as joint organizers of the universe. If we
look back on the history of the exact sciences, it can perhaps be
asserted that the correct representations of natural phenomena has
evolved from this very tension between the two opposing views. Pure
mathematical speculation becomes unfruitful because from playing with
the wealth of possible forms it no longer finds its way back to the
small number of forms according to which nature is actually constructed.
And pure empiricism becomes unfruitful because it eventually bogs down
in endless tabulation without inner connection. Only from the tension,
the interplay between the wealth of facts and the mathematical forms
that may possibly be appropriate to them, can decisive advances spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in antiquity this tension was no longer acceptable and thus, the
road to knowledge diverged for a long time from the road to the
beautiful. The significance of the beautiful for the understanding of
nature became clearly visible again only at the beginning of the modern
period, once the way back had been found from Aristotle to Plato. And
only through this change of course did the full fruitfulness become
apparent of the mode of thought inaugurated by Pythagoras and Plato.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_432" align="alignright" width="445"
caption="Galileo Galilei, Istoria e Dimonstrazioni (Rome, 1613),
Frontispiece"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Galileo-Frontispiece.jpg" title="Galileo Galilei, Istoria e Dimonstrazioni (Rome, 1613), Frontispiece" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is most clearly shown in the celebrated experiments on falling
bodies that Galileo probably did not, in fact, conduct from the leaning
tower of Pisa. Galileo begins with careful observations, paying no
attention to the authority of Aristotle, but, following the teaching of
Pythagoras and Plato, he does try to find mathematical forms
corresponding to the facts obtained by experiment and thus, arrives at
his laws of falling bodies. However, and this is a crucial point, he is
obliged, in order to recognize the beauty of mathematical forms in the
phenomena, to idealize the facts, or, as Aristotle disparagingly puts
it, to force them. Aristotle had taught that all moving bodies not acted
upon by external forces eventually come to rest, and this was the
general experience. Galileo maintains, on the contrary, that, in the
absence of external forces, bodies continue in a state of uniform
motion. Galileo could venture to force the facts in this way because he
could point out that moving bodies are, of course, always exposed to a
frictional resistance and that motion, in fact, continues the longer,
the more effectively the frictional forces can be cut off. In exchange
for this forcing of the facts, this idealization, he obtained a simple
mathematical law, and this was the beginning of modern exact science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years later, Kepler succeeded in discovering new mathematical forms
in the data of his very careful observations of the planetary orbits and
in formulating the three famous laws that bear his name. How close
Kepler felt himself in these discoveries to the ancient arguments of
Pythagoras, and how much the beauty of the connections guided him in
formulating them, can be seen from the fact that he compared the
revolutions of the planets about the sun with the vibrations of a string
and spoke of a harmonious concord of the different planetary orbits, of
a harmony of spheres. At the end of his work on the harmony of the
universe, he broke out into this cry of joy: “I thank thee, Lord God our
Creator, that thou allowest me to see the beauty in thy work of
creation.” Kepler was profoundly struck by the fact that here he had
chanced upon a central connection which had not been conceived by man,
which it had been reserved to him to recognize for the first time—a
connection of the highest beauty. A few decades later, Isaac Newton in
England set forth this connection in all its completeness and described
it in detail in his great work &lt;em&gt;Principia Mathematica&lt;/em&gt;. The road of
exact science was thus pointed out in advance for almost two centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But are we dealing here with knowledge merely, or also with the
beautiful? And if the beautiful is also involved, what role did it play
in the discovery of these connections? Let us again recall the first
definition given in antiquity: “Beauty is the proper conformity of the
parts to one another and to the whole.” That this criterion applies in
the highest degree to a structure like Newtonian mechanics is something
that scarcely needs explaining. The parts are the individual mechanical
processes—those which we carefully isolate by means of apparatus no less
than those which occur inextricably before our eyes in the colorful play
of phenomena. And the whole is the unitary principle of form which all
these processes comply with and which was mathematically established by
Newton in a simple system of axioms. Unity and simplicity are not,
indeed, precisely the same. But the fact that in such a theory the many
are confronted with the one, that in it the many are unified, itself has
the undoubted consequence that we also feel it at the same time to be
simple and beautiful. The significance of the beautiful for the
discovery of the true has at all times been recognized and emphasized.
The Latin motto &lt;em&gt;“Simplex sigillum veri”&lt;/em&gt;—“The simple is the seal of the
true”—is inscribed in large letters in the physics auditorium of the
University of Göttingen as an admonition to those who would discover
what is new; another Latin motto, &lt;em&gt;“Pulchritudo splendor
veritatis”&lt;/em&gt;—“Beauty is the splendor of truth”—can also be interpreted to
mean that the researcher first recognizes truth by this splendor, by the
way it shines forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twice more in the history of exact science, this shining forth of the
great connection has been the crucial signal for a significant advance.
I am thinking here of two events in the physics of our own century: the
emergence of relativity theory and quantum theory. In both cases, after
years of vain effort at understanding, a bewildering plethora of details
has been almost suddenly reduced to order by the appearance of a
connection, largely unintuitable but still ultimately simple in its
substance, that was immediately found convincing by virtue of its
completeness and abstract beauty—convincing, that is, to all who could
understand and speak such an abstract language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, instead of pursuing the historical course of events any
further, let us rather put the question quite directly: What is it that
shines forth here? How comes it that with this shining forth of the
beautiful into exact science the great connection becomes recognizable,
even before it is understood in detail and before it can be rationally
demonstrated? In what does the power of illumination consist, and what
effect does it have on the onward progress of science?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we should begin here by recalling a phenomenon that may be
described as the unfolding of abstract structures. It can be illustrated
by the example of number theory, which we referred to at the outset, but
one may also point to comparable processes in the evolution of art. For
the mathematical foundation of arithmetic, or the theory of numbers, a
few simple axioms are sufficient, which, in fact, merely define exactly
what counting is. But with these few axioms we have already posited that
whole abundance of forms which has entered the minds of mathematicians
only in the course of the long history of the subject—the theory of
prime numbers, of quadratic residues, of numerical congruences, etc. One
might say that the abstract structures posited in and with numbers have
unfolded visibly only in the course of mathematical history, that they
have generated the wealth of propositions and relationships that makes
up the content of the complicated science of number theory. A similar
position is also occupied—at the outset of an artistic style in
architecture, say—by certain simple basic forms, such as the semicircle
and rectangle in Romanesque architecture. From these basic forms there
arise in the course of history new, more complicated, and also altered
forms, which yet can still, in some way, be regarded as variations on
the same theme; thus, from the basic structures there emerges a new
manner, a new style of building. We have the feeling, nonetheless, that
the possibilities of development were already perceivable in these
original forms, even at the outset; otherwise, it would be scarcely
comprehensible that many gifted artists should have so quickly resolved
to pursue these new possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_433" align="alignleft" width="346" caption="The
Page from Isaac Newton's Folios On Which He Predicts The Apocalypse
Would Come As Early As A.D. 2132"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/The-Page-from-Isaac-Newtons-Folios-On-Which-He-Predicts-The-Apocalypse-Would-Come-As-Early-As-A.D.-2132.jpg" title="The Page from Isaac Newton's Folios On Which He Predicts The Apocalypse Would Come As Early As A.D. 2132" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an unfolding of abstract basic structures has assuredly also
occurred in the instances I have enumerated from the history of the
exact sciences. This growth, this constant development of new branches,
went on in Newtonian mechanics up to the middle of the last century. In
relativity theory and the quantum theory we have experienced a similar
development in the present century, and the growth has not yet come to
an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, in science, as in art, this process also has an important
social and ethical aspect; for many men can take an active part in it.
When a great cathedral was to be built in the Middle Ages, many master
masons and craftsmen were employed. They were imbued with the idea of
beauty posited by the original forms and were compelled by their task to
carry out exact and meticulous work in accordance with these forms. In
similar fashion, during the two centuries following Newton's discovery,
many mathematicians, physicists, and technicians were called upon to
deal with specific mechanical problems according to the Newtonian
methods, to carry out experiments, or to effect technical applications;
here, too, extreme care was always required in order to attain what was
possible within the framework of Newtonian mechanics. Perhaps it may be
said in general that by means of the underlying structures, in this case
Newtonian mechanics, guidelines were drawn or even standards of value
set up whereby it could be objectively decided whether a given task had
been well or ill discharged. It is the very fact that specific
requirements have been laid down, that the individual can assist by
small contributions in the attainment of large goals, and that the value
of his contribution can be objectively determined, which gives rise to
the satisfaction proceeding from such a development for the large number
of people involved. Hence even the ethical significances of technology
for our present age should not be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of science and technology has also produced, for
example, the Idea of the airplane. The individual technician who
assembles some component for such a plane, the artisan who makes it,
knows that his work calls for the utmost care and exactitude and that
the lives of many may well depend upon its reliability. Hence he can
take pride in a well-executed piece of work, and delights, as we do, in
the beauty of the aircraft, when he feels that in it the technical goal
has been realized by properly adequate means. Beauty, so runs the
ancient definition we have often cited, is the proper conformity of the
parts to one another and to the whole, and this requirement must also be
satisfied in a good aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in pointing thus to the evolution of beauty's ground structure, to
the ethical values and demands that subsequently emerge in the
historical course of development, we have not yet answered the question
we asked earlier, namely, what it is that shines forth in these
structures, how the great connection is recognized even before it is
rationally understood in detail. Here we ought to reckon in advance with
the possibility that even such recognition may be founded upon
illusions. But it cannot be doubted that there actually is this
perfectly immediate recognition, this shuddering before the beautiful,
of which Plato speaks in the &lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among those who have pondered on this question, it seems to have been
universally agreed that this immediate recognition is not a consequence
of the discursive (i.e. rational) thinking. I should like here to cite
two statements, on from Johannes Kepler, who has already been referred
to, and the other, in our own time, from the Zürich atomic physicist
Wolfgang Pauli, who was a friend of the psychologist, Carl Jung. The
first passage is to be found in Kepler's &lt;em&gt;Harmony of the World&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_434" align="alignleft" width="300"
caption="Kepler, Harmonium Mundis, Frontispiece"][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/kepler_harmonium-mundis-frontpiece.jpg" title="Kepler, Harmonium Mundis, Frontispiece" /&gt;][][/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far Kepler. He is, therefore, referring us here to possibilities
already to be found in the animal and plant kingdoms, to innate
archetypes that bring about the recognition of forms. In our own day,
Adolf Portmann, in particular, has described such possibilities,
pointing, for example, to specific color patterns seen in the plumage of
birds, which can possess a biological meaning only if they are also
perceived by other members of the same species. The perceptual capacity
will therefore have to be just as innate as the pattern itself. We may
also consider bird song at this point. At first, the biological
requirement here may well have been simply for a specific acoustic
signal, serving to seek out the partner and understood by the latter.
But to the extent that this immediate biological function declines in
importance, a playful enlargement of the stock of forms may ensue, and
unfolding of the underlying melodic structure, which is then found
enchanting as song by even so alien a species as man. The capacity to
recognize this play of forms must, at all events, be innate to the
species of bird in question for certainly it has no need of discursive,
rational capacity for understanding certain basic forms of the language
of gesture and thus, for deciding, say, whether the other has friendly
or hostile intentions—a capacity of the utmost importance for man's
communal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideas similar to those of Kepler have been put forward in an essay by
Pauli. He writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The process of understanding in nature, together with the joy that man
feels in understanding, i.e., in becoming acquainted with new knowledge,
seems therefore to rest upon a correspondence, a coming into congruence
of preexistent internal images of the human psyche with external objects
and their behavior. This view of natural knowledge goes back, of course,
to Plato and was...also very plainly adopted by Kepler. The latter
speaks, in fact, of Ideas, preexistent in the mind of God and imprinted
accordingly upon the soul, as the image of God. These primal images,
which the soul can perceive by means of an innate instinct, Kepler calls
archetypes. There is very wide-ranging agreement here with the
primordial images or archetypes introduced into modern psychology by C.
G. Jung, which function as instinctive patterns of ideation. At this
stage, the place of clear concepts is taken by images of strongly
emotional content, which are not thought but are seen pictorially, as it
were, before the mind's eye. Insofar as these images are the expression
of a suspected but still unknown state of affairs, they can also be
called symbolic, according to the definition of a symbol proposed by
Jung. As ordering operators and formatives in this world of symbolic
images, the archetypes function, indeed, as the desired bridge between
sense perceptions and Ideas, and are therefore also a necessary
precondition for the emergence of a scientific theory. Yet one must
beware of displacing this&lt;/em&gt;a priori &lt;em&gt;knowledge into consciousness, and
relating it to specific, rationally formulable Ideas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the further course of his inquiries, Pauli then goes on to show that
Kepler did not derive his conviction of the correctness of the
Copernican system primarily from any particular data of astronomical
observation, but rather from the agreement of the Copernican picture
with an archetype which Jung calls a &lt;em&gt;mandala&lt;/em&gt; and which was also used
by Kepler as a symbol for the Trinity. God, as prime mover, is seen at
the center of a sphere; the world, in which the Son works, is compared
with the sphere's surface; the Holy Ghost corresponds to the beams that
radiate from center to surface of the sphere. It is naturally
characteristic of these primal images that they cannot really be
rationally or even intuitively described.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Kepler may have acquired his conviction of the correctness of
Copernicanism from primal images of this kind, it remains a crucial
precondition for any usable scientific theory that it should
subsequently stand up to empirical testing and rational analysis. In
this respect, the sciences are in a happier position than the arts,
since for science there is an inexorable and irrevocable criterion of
value that no piece of work can evade. The Copernican system, the
Keplerian laws, and the Newtonian mechanics have subsequently proved
themselves—in the interpreting of phenomena, in observational findings,
and in technology—over such a range and with such extreme accuracy that
after Newton's &lt;em&gt;Principia&lt;/em&gt; it was no longer possible to doubt that they
were correct. Yet even here there was still an idealization involved,
such as Plato had held necessary and Aristotle had disapproved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This only came out in full clarity some fifty years ago when it was
realized from the findings in atomic physics that the Newtonian scheme
of concepts was no longer adequate to cope with the mechanical phenomena
in the interior of the atom. Since Planck's discovery of the quantum of
action, in 1900, a state of confusion had arisen in physics. The old
rules, whereby nature had been successfully described for more than two
century, would no longer fit the new findings. But even these findings
were themselves inherently contradictory. A hypothesis that proved
itself in one experiment failed in another. The beauty and completeness
of the old physics seemed destroyed, without anyone having been able,
from the often disparate experiments, to gain a real insight into new
and different sorts of connection. I don't know if it is fitting to
compare the state of physics in those twenty-five years after Planck's
discovery (which I, too, encountered as a young student) to the
circumstances of contemporary modern art. But I have to confess that
this comparison repeatedly comes to mind. The helplessness when faced
with the question of what to do about the bewildering phenomena, the
lamenting over lost connections, which still continue to look very
convincing—all these discontents have shaped the face of both
disciplines and both periods, different as they are, in a similar
manner. We are obviously concerned here with a necessary intervening
stage, which cannot be bypassed and which is preparing for developments
to come. For, as Pauli told us, all understanding is a protracted
affair, inaugurated by processes in the unconscious long before the
content of consciousness can be rationally formulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment, however, when the true Ideas rise up, there occurs in
the soul of him who sees them an altogether indescribable process of the
highest intensity. It is the amazed awe the Plato speaks of in the
&lt;em&gt;Phaedrus&lt;/em&gt;, with which the soul remembers, as it were, something it had
unconsciously possessed all along. Kepler says: &lt;em&gt;“Geometria est
archetypus pulchritudinis mundi”&lt;/em&gt;; or, if we may translate in more
general terms: “Mathematics is the archetype of the beauty of the
world.” In atomic physics this process took place not quite fifty years
ago and has again restored exact science, under entirely new
presuppositions, to that state of harmonious completeness which for a
quarter of a century it had lost. I see no reason why the same thing
should not also happen one day in art. But it must be added, by way of
warning, that such a thing cannot be made to happen—it has to occur on
its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have set this aspect of exact science before you because in it the
affinity with the fine arts becomes most plainly visible and because
here one may counter the misapprehension that natural science and
technology are concerned solely with precise observation and rational,
discursive thought. To be sure, this rational thinking and careful
measurement belong to the scientist's work, just as the hammer and the
chisel belong to the work of the sculptor. But in both cases they are
merely the tools and not the content of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps at the very end I may remind you once more of the second
definition of the concept of beauty, which stems from Plotinus and in
which no more is heard of the parts and the whole: “Beauty is the
translucence, through the material phenomenon, of the eternal splendor
of the 'one.'” There are important periods of art in which this
definition is more appropriate than the first, and to such periods we
often look longingly back. But in our own time it is hard to speak of
beauty from this aspect, and perhaps it is a good rule to adhere to the
custom of the age one has to live in, and to keep silent about that
which it is difficult to say. In fact, the two definitions are not so
very widely removed from one another. So let us be content with the
first and more sober definition of beauty, which certainly is also
realized in natural science, and let us declare that in exact science,
no less than in the arts, it is the most important source of
illumination and clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Ohioan-Native-Kin.jpg" title="Ohioan &amp;amp; Native Kin" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Ohioan-Native-Kin.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Heisenberg.jpg" title="Heisenberg" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Heisenberg.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/pythagoras1.jpg" title="Pythagoras" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/pythagoras1.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Plato_1_lg.gif" title="Plato" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Plato_1_lg.gif
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Galileo-Frontispiece.jpg" title="Galileo Galilei, Istoria e Dimonstrazioni (Rome, 1613), Frontispiece" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Galileo-Frontispiece.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/The-Page-from-Isaac-Newtons-Folios-On-Which-He-Predicts-The-Apocalypse-Would-Come-As-Early-As-A.D.-2132.jpg" title="The Page from Isaac Newton's Folios On Which He Predicts The Apocalypse Would Come As Early As A.D. 2132" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/The-Page-from-Isaac-Newtons-Folios-On-Which-He-Predicts-The-Apocalypse-Would-Come-As-Early-As-A.D.-2132.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/kepler_harmonium-mundis-frontpiece.jpg" title="Kepler, Harmonium Mundis, Frontispiece" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/kepler_harmonium-mundis-frontpiece.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Ancient Greek philosophy"></category><category term="aristotle"></category><category term="beauty"></category><category term="Democritus"></category><category term="experimental music"></category><category term="Isaac Newton"></category><category term="johannes kepler"></category><category term="Ohioan"></category><category term="Parmenides"></category><category term="plato"></category><category term="Plotinus"></category><category term="Pythagoras"></category><category term="quantum physics"></category><category term="ryne warner"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="Werner Heisenberg"></category></entry><entry><title>Famous Physicists on Mysticism #2: "The Debate Between Plato and Democritus" by Werner Heisenberg</title><link href="/famous-physicists-on-mysticism-2-the-debate-between-plato-and-democritus-by-werner-heisenberg.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-18T15:28:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2010-09-18:famous-physicists-on-mysticism-2-the-debate-between-plato-and-democritus-by-werner-heisenberg.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://en.citizendium.org/images/thumb/e/e2/Caelestiall_orbes.jpeg/350px-Caelestiall_orbes.jpeg" title="Orbital Structures of Pythagoreans" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was here in this part of the world, on the coast of the Aegean Sea,
that the philosophers Leucippus and Democritus pondered about the
structure of matter, and down there in the marketplace, where twilight
is now falling, that Socrates disputed about the basic difficulties in
our modes of expression and Plato taught that the Idea, the form, was
the truly fundamental pattern behind the phenomena. The problems first
formulated in this country two and a half thousand years ago have
occupied the human mind almost unceasingly ever since and have been
discussed again and again in the course of history whenever new
developments have altered the light in which the old lines of thought
appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I endeavor today to take up some of the old problems concerning the
structure of matter and the concept of natural law, it is because the
development of atomic physics in out own day has radically altered our
whole outlook on nature and the structure of matter. It is perhaps not
an improper exaggeration to maintain that some of the old problems have
quite recently found a clear and final solution. So it is permissible
today to speak about this new and perhaps conclusive answer to questions
that were formulated here thousands of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, however, yet another reason for renewing consideration of
these problems. The philosophy of materialism, developed in antiquity by
Leucippus and Democritus, has been the subject of many discussions since
the rise of modern science in the seventeenth century and, in the form
of dialectical materialism, has been one of the moving forces in the
political changes of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. If
philosophical ideas about the structure of matter have been able to play
such a role in human life, if in European society they have operated
almost like an explosive and may yet perhaps do so in other parts of the
world, it is even more important to know what our present scientific
knowledge has to say about this philosophy. To put it in rather general
and precise terms, we may hope that a philosophical analysis of recent
scientific developments will contribute to a replacement of conflicting
dogmatic opinions about the basic problems we have broached, by a sober
readjustment to a new situation, which, in itself, can even now be
regarded as a revolution in human life on this earth. But even aside
from this influence of science upon our time, it may be of interest to
compare the philosophical discussions in ancient Greece with the
findings of experimental science and modern atomic physics. If I may
already anticipate at this point the outcome of such a comparison; it
seems that, in spite of the tremendous success that the concept of the
atom has achieved in modern science, Plato was very much nearer to the
truth about the structure of matter than Leucippus or Democritus. But it
will doubtless be necessary to begin by repeating some of the most
important arguments adduced in the ancient discussions about matter and
life, being and becoming, before we can enter into the findings of
modern science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Concept of Matter in Ancient Philosophy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of Greek philosophy there stood the dilemma of the
“one” and the “many.” We know that there is an ever-changing variety of
phenomena appearing to our senses. Yet we believe that ultimately it
should be possible to trace them back somehow to some one principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founders of atomism, Leucippus and Democritus, tried to avoid the
difficulty by assuming the atom to be eternal and indestructible, the
only thing really existing. All other things exist only because they are
composed of atoms. The antithesis of “being” and “non being” in the
philosophy of Parmenides is here coarsened into that between the “full”
and the “void.” Being is not only one; it can be repeated infinitely
many times. Being is indestructible, and therefore the atom, too, is
indestructible. The void, the empty space between the atoms, allows for
position and motion, and thus for properties of the atom, whereas by
definition, as it were, pure being can have no other property than that
of existence. This latter part of the doctrine of Leucippus and
Democritus is at once its strength and its weakness. On the one hand, it
provides an immediate explanation of the different aggregate states of
matter, such as ice, water, and steam, since the atoms may lie densely
packed and in order beside each other, or be caught in disorder and
irregular motion, or finally be separated at fairly large relative
intervals in space. This part of the atomic hypothesis was therefore to
prove exceedingly fruitful at a later stage. One the other hand, the
atom becomes in this fashion a mere building block of matter; its
properties, position, and motion in space turn it into something quite
different from what was meant by the original concept of “being.” The
atoms can even have a finite extension, and here we have finally lost
the only convincing argument for their indivisibility. If the atom has
spacial properties, why should it not be divided? At least its
indivisibility then becomes a physical, not a fundamental property. We
can now again ask questions about the structure of the atom, and we run
the risk of losing all the simplicity we had hoped to find among the
smallest parts of matter. We get the impression, therefore, that in its
original form the atomic hypothesis was not sufficiently subtle to
explain what the philosophers really wished to understand: the simple
element in the phenomena and in the structure of matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the atomic hypothesis does go a large part of the way in the
right direction. The whole multiplicity of diverse phenomena, the man
observed properties of matter, can be reduced to the position and motion
of the atoms. Properties such as smell or color or taste are not present
in atoms. But their position and motion can evoke these properties
indirectly. Position and motion seem to be much simpler concepts than
the empirical qualities of taste, smell, or color. But then it naturally
remains to ask what determines the position and motion of the atoms. The
Greek philosophers did not attempt at this point to formulate a law of
nature; the modern concept of natural law did not fit into their way of
thought. Yet they seem to have thought of some kind of causal
description or determinism, since they spoke of necessity, of cause and
effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intention of the atomic hypothesis had been to point the way from
the “many” to the “one,” to formulate the underlying principle, the
material cause, by virtue of which all phenomena can be understood. The
atoms could be regarded as the material cause, but only a general law
determining their positions and velocities could actually play the part
of the fundamental principle. However, when the Greek philosophers
discussed the laws of nature, their thoughts were directed to static
forms, geometrical symmetries, rather than to processes of space and
time. The circular orbits of the planets, the regular geometrical
solids, appeared to be the permanent structures of the world. The modern
idea, that the position and velocity of the atom at a given time could
be uniquely connected by a mathematical law with its position and
velocity at a later time, did not fit into the pattern of thought of
that era since it employs the concept of time in a manner that arose
only out the the thinking of a much later epoch.&lt;img alt="" src="http://i36.tinypic.com/fyd0mg.jpg" title="Platonic solids and elements" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Plato himself took up the problems raised by Leucippus and
Democritus, he adopted the idea of smallest units of matter, but he took
the strongest exception to the tendency of that philosophy to suppose
the atoms to be the foundation of all existence, the only truly existing
material objects. Plato's atoms were not strictly material, being
thought of as geometrical forms, the regular solids of the
mathematicians. These bodies, in keeping with the starting point of his
idealistic philosophy, were in some sense the Ideas underlying the
structure of matter and characterizing the physical behavior of the
elements to which they belonged. The cube, for example, was the smallest
particle of the element earth and thereby symbolized at the same time
the earth's stability. The tetrahedron, with its sharp point,
represented the smallest particle of the element fire. The icosahedron,
which comes closest among the regular solids to a sphere, stood for the
mobility of the element water. In this way the regular solids were able
to serve as symbols for certain tendencies in the physical behavior of
matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they were not strictly atoms, not indivisible basic units like those
of the materialist philosophy. Plato regarded then as composed from the
triangles forming their surfaces; therefore, by exchanging triangles,
these smallest particles could be commuted into each other. Thus two
atoms of air, for example, and one of fire could be compounded into an
atom of water. In this was Plato was able to escape the problem of the
indefinite divisibility of matter. For as two-dimensional surfaces the
triangles were not bodies, not matter any longer; hance matter could not
be further divided ad infinitum. At the lower end, therefore, in the
realm, that is, of minimal spatial dimensions, the concept of matter is
resolved into that of mathematical form. This form determines the
behavior, first of the smallest parts of matter, then of matter itself.
To a certain extent it replaces the natural law of later physics; for
without making explicit references to the course of time, it
characterizes the tendencies in the behavior of matter. One might say,
perhaps, that the fundamental tendencies were represented by the
geometrical shape of the smallest units, while the finer details of
those tendencies found expression in the relative position and velocity
of these units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole description fits exactly into the central ideas of Plato's
idealist philosophy. The structure underlying the phenomena is not given
by material objects like the atoms of Democritus but by the form that
determines the material objects. The Ideas are more fundamental then the
objects. And since the smallest parts of matter have to be the objects
whereby the simplicity of the world becomes visible, whereby we
approximate to the “one” and the “unity” of the world, the Ideas can be
described mathematically—they are simply mathematical forms. The saying
“God is a mathematician,” which in this form assuredly derives from a
later period of philosophy, has its origin in this passage from the
Platonic philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of this step in philosophical thought can hardly be
reckoned too highly. It can be seen as the decisive beginning of the
mathematical science of nature, and hence be made responsible also for
the later technical applications that have altered the whole picture of
the world. By this step it is also first established what the term
“understanding” is to mean. Among all the possible forms of
understanding. Whereas all language, indeed, al art and all poetry in
some way mediate understanding, it is here maintained that only the
employment of a precise, logically consistent language, a language so
far capable of formalization that proofs become possible, can lead to
true understanding. One feels the strength of the impression made upon
the Greek philosophers by the persuasive force of logical and
mathematical arguments. They are obviously overwhelmed by this force.
But perhaps they surrendered too early at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Answer of Modern Science to the Old Problems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we trace the history of physics from Newton to the present day, we
see that, despite the interest in details, very general laws of mature
have been formulated on several occasions. The nineteenth century saw an
exact working out of the statistical theory of heat. The theories of
electromagnetism and special relativity have proved susceptible of
combination into a very general group of natural laws containing
statements not only about electrical phenomena but also about the
structure of space and time. In our own century, the mathematical
formulation of the quantum theory has led to an understanding of the
outer shells of chemical atoms, and thus of the chemical properties of
matter generally. The relations and connections between these different
laws, especially between relativity and quantum theory, are not yet
fully explained. But the latest developments in particle physics permit
one to hope that these relations may be satisfactorily analyzed in the
relatively near future. We are thus already in a position to consider
what answers can be given by this whole scientific development to the
questions of the old philosophers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the nineteenth century, the development of chemistry and the
theory of heat conformed very closely tot he ideas first put forward by
Leucippus and Democritus. A revival of the materialist philosophy in its
modern form, that of dialectical materialism, was this a natural
counterpart to the impressive advances made during this period in
chemistry and physics. The concept of the atom had proved exceptionally
fruitful in the explanation of chemical bonding and the physical
behavior of gases. It was soon, however, that the particles called atoms
by the chemist were composed of still smaller units. But these smaller
units, the electrons, followed by the atomic nuclei and finally the
elementary particles, protons and neutrons, also still seemed to be
atoms from the standpoint of the materialist philosophy. The fact that,
at least indirectly, one can actually see a single elementary
particle—in a cloud chamber, say, or a bubble chamber—supports the view
that the smallest units of matter are real physical objects, existing in
the same sense that stones or flowers do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the inherent difficulties of the materialist theory of the atom,
which had become apparent even in the ancient discussions about smallest
particles, have also appeared very clearly in the development of physics
during the present century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This difficulty relates to the question whether the smallest units are
ordinary physical objects, whether they exist in the same way as stones
or flowers. Here, the development of quantum theory some forty years ago
has created a complete change in the situation. The mathematically
formulated laws of quantum theory show clearly that our ordinary
intuitive concepts cannot be unambiguously applied to the smallest
particles. All the words or concepts we use to describe ordinary
physical objects, such as position, velocity, color, size, and so on,
become indefinite and problematic if we try to use then of elementary
particles. I cannot enter here into the details of this problem, which
has been discussed so frequently in recent years. But it is important to
realize that, while the behavior of the smallest particles cannot be
unambiguously described in ordinary language, the language of
mathematics is still adequate for a clear-cut account of what is going
on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the coming years, the high-energy accelerators will bring to
light many further interesting details about the behavior of elementary
particles. But I am inclined to think that the answer just considered to
the old philosophical problems will turn out to be final. If this is so,
does this answer confirm the views of Democritus or Plato?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that on this point modern physics has definitely decided for
Plato. For the smallest units of matter are, in fact, not physical
objects in the ordinary sense of the word; they are forms, structures
or—in Plato's sense—Ideas, which can be unambiguously spoken of only in
the language of mathematics. Democritus and Plato both had hoped that in
the smallest units of matter they would be approaching the “one,” the
unitary principle that governs the course of the world. Plato was
convinced that this principle can be expressed and understood only in
mathematical form. The central problem of theoretical physics nowadays
is the mathematical formulation of the natural law underlying the
behavior of elementary particles. From the experimental situation we
infer that a satisfactory theory of the elementary particles must at the
same time be a theory of physics in general, and hence, of everything
else belonging to this physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, a program could be carried out that in modern times was
first proposed by Einstein: a unified theory of matter—and hence,
simultaneously, a quantum theory of matter—could be formulated, which
might serve quite generally as a foundation for physics. We do not yet
know whether the mathematical forms proposed for this unifying principle
are already adequate or will have to be replaced by forms more abstract
still. But our present knowledge of the elementary particles is
certainly enough for us to say what the main content of this law has to
be. It must essentially set forth a small number of fundamental symmetry
properties in nature, which have been known empirically for some years;
in addition to these symmetries, it must contain the principle of
causality as understood in relativity theory. The most important of the
symmetries are the so-called “Lorentz group” of space and time, and the
so-called “isospin group,” which has to do with the electric charge on
the elementary particles. There are also other symmetries, but of these
I shall say nothing here. Relativistic causality is connected with the
Lorentz group but must be considered an independent principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This situation reminds us at once of the symmetrical bodies introduced
by Plato to represent the fundamental structures of matter. Plato's
symmetries were not yet the correct ones, but he was right in believing
that ultimately, at the heart of nature, among the smallest units of
matter, we find mathematical symmetries. It was an unbelievable
achievement of the ancient philosophers to have asked the right
questions. But, lacking all knowledge of the empirical details, we could
not have expected them to find answers that were correct in detail as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequences for the Evolution of Human Thought in Our Own Day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The search for the “one,” for the ultimate source of all understanding,
has doubtless played a similar role in the origin of both religion and
science. But the scientific method that was developed in the sixteenth
and seventeenth centuries, the interest in those details which can be
tested by experiment, has for a long time pointed science along a
different path. It is not surprising that this attitude should have led
to a conflict between science and religion, as soon as a law
contradicted, in some particular and perhaps very important detail, the
general picture, the mode and manner, in which the facts had been spoken
of in religion. This conflict, which began in modern times with the
celebrated trial of Galileo, has been discussed often enough, and I need
not repeat this discussion here. One may recall that, even in ancient
Greece, Socrates was condemned to death because his teachings seemed to
contradict the traditional religion. In the nineteenth century, this
conflict reached its peak in the attempt of some philosophers to replace
traditional Christianity by a scientific philosophy, based upon a
materialist version of the Hegelian dialectic. It might be said that, in
directing their gaze upon a materialistic interpretation of the “one,”
the scientists were attempting to find their way back again to this
“one” from the multitude of details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If modern science has something to contribute to this problem, it is not
by deciding for or against one of these doctrines; for example, as was
possibly believed in the nineteenth century, by coming down in favor of
materialism and against the Christian philosophy, or, as I now believe,
in favor of Plato's idealism and against the materialism of Democritus.
On the contrary, the chief profit we can derive in these problems from
the progress of modern science is to learn how cautious we have to be
with language and with the meaning of words. I would therefore like to
devote the last part of my address to a few remarks about the problem of
language in modern science and ancient philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we may take our cue at this point from Plato's dialogues, the
unavoidable limitations of our means of expression were already a
central theme in the philosophy of Socrates; one might even say that his
whole life was a constant battle with these limitations. Socrates never
wearied of explaining to his countrymen, here on the streets of Athens.
That they did not know exactly what they meant by the words they were
employing. The story goes that one of Socrates' opponents, a sophist who
was annoyed at Socrates' constant reference to this insufficiency of
language, criticized him and said: “But Socrates, this is a bore; you
are always saying the same about the same.” Socrates replied: “But you
sophists, who are so clever, perhaps never say the same about the same.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for laying such stress on this problem of language was
doubtless that Socrates was aware, on the one hand, of how many
misunderstandings can be engendered by a careless use of language, how
important it is to use precise terms and to elucidate concepts before
employing them. One the other hand, he probably also realized that this
may ultimately be an insoluble task. The situation confronting us in our
attempt to “understand” may drive us to conclude that our existing means
of expression do not allow for a clear and unambiguous description of
the facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tension between the demand for complete clarity and the inevitable
inadequacy of existing concepts has been especially marked in modern
science. In atomic physics we make use of a highly developed
mathematical language that satisfies all the requirements in regard to
clarity and precision. At the same time, we recognize that we cannot
describe atomic phenomena without ambiguity in any ordinary language; we
cannot, for example, speak unambiguously about the behavior of an
electron in the interior of an atom. It would premature, however, to
insist that we should avoid the difficulty by confining ourselves to the
use of mathematical language. This is no genuine way out, since we do
not know how far the mathematical language can be applied to phenomena.
In the last resort, even science must rely upon ordinary language, since
it is the only language in which we can be sure of really grasping the
phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This situation throws some light on the tension between the scientific
method, on the one hand, and the relation of society to the “one,” the
fundamental principle behind phenomena, on the other. It seems obvious
that this latter relation cannot and should not be expressed in a
precise and highly sophisticated language whose applicability to the
real world may be very restricted. The only thing that will do for this
purpose is the natural language everyone can understand. Reliable
results in science, however, can be secured only by unambiguous
statement; here we cannot do without the precision and clarity of an
abstract mathematical language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The necessity of constantly shuttling between the two languages is,
unfortunately, a chronic source of misunderstandings, since in many
cases the same words are employed in both. The difficulty is
unavoidable. But it may yet be of some help always to bear in mind that
modern science is obliged to make use of both languages, that the same
word may have very different meanings in each of them, that different
criteria of truth apply, and that one should not, therefore, talk too
hastily of contradictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we wish to approach the “one” in the terms of a precise scientific
language, we must turn our attention to that center of science described
by Plato, in which the fundamental mathematical symmetries are to be
found. In the concepts of this language we must be content with the
statement that “God is a mathematician”; for we have freely chosen to
confine our vision to that realm of being which can be understood in the
mathematical sense of the word “understanding,” which can be described
in rational terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plato himself was not content with this restriction. Having pointed out
with the utmost clarity the possibilities and limitations of precise
language, he switched to the language of poetry, which evokes in the
hearer images conveying understanding of an altogether different kind. I
shall not seek to discuss here what this kind of understanding can
really mean. These images are probably connected with the unconscious
mental patterns the psychologists speak of as archetypes, forms of
strongly emotional character that, in some way, reflect the internal
structures of the world. But whatever the explanation for these other
forms of understanding, the language of images and likenesses is
probably the only way of approaching the “one” from more general
domains. If the harmony in a society rests on a common interpretation of
the “one,” the unitary principle behind the phenomena, then the language
of poetry may be more important here than the language of science.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Democritus"></category><category term="geometry"></category><category term="idealism"></category><category term="language"></category><category term="mysticism"></category><category term="plato"></category><category term="quantum physics"></category><category term="Socrates"></category><category term="Werner Heisenberg"></category></entry><entry><title>Famous Physicists On Mysticism #1: "Scientific and Religious Truths" by Werner Heisenberg</title><link href="/famous-physicists-on-mysticism-1-scientific-and-religious-truths-by-werner-heisenberg.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-11T21:52:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2010-09-11:famous-physicists-on-mysticism-1-scientific-and-religious-truths-by-werner-heisenberg.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is going to be an ongoing reprint series of mystical writings by
famous physicists. The view expressed herein are presented merely for
consideration and are not necessarily those of the blogger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="" align="alignright" width="280" caption="Werner
Heisenberg"]&lt;img alt="" src="http://reich-chemistry.wikispaces.com/file/view/HSwerner.jpg/31485803/HSwerner.jpg" title="Werner Heisenberg" /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific and Religious Truths&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Werner Heisenberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the history of science, ever since the famous trial of Galileo, it
has repeatedly been claimed that scientific truth cannot be reconciled
with the religious interpretation of the world. Although I an now
convinced that scientific truth is unassailable in its own field, I have
never found it possible to dismiss the content of religious thinking as
simply part of an outmoded phase in the consciousness of mankind, a part
we shall have to give up from now on, Thus in the course of my life I
have repeatedly been compelled to ponder on the relationship of these
two regions of though, for I have never been able to doubt the reality
of that to which they point. In what follows, then, we shall first of
all deal with the unassailability and value of scientific truth, and
then with the much wider field of religion; finally—and this will be the
hardest part to formulate—we shall speak of the relationship of the two
truths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the beginnings of modern science, the discoveries of Copernicus,
Galileo, Kepler, and Newton, it is usually said that the truth of
religious revelation, laid down in the Bible and the writings of the
Church Fathers and dominant in the thought of the Middle Ages, was at
that time supplemented by the reality of sensory experience, which could
be checked by anyone in possession of his normal five senses and
which—if enough care was taken—could, therefore, not in the end be
doubted. But even this first approach to a description of the new way of
thought is only half correct; it neglects decisive features without
which its power cannot be understood. It is certainly no accident that
the beginnings of modern science were associated with a turning away
from Aristotle and a reversion to Plato. Even in antiquity, Aristotle,
as an empiricist, had raised the objection—I cite more or less his own
words—that the Pythagoreans (among whom Plato must be included) did not
seek for explanations and theories to suit the facts, but distorted the
facts to fit certain theories and favored opinions, and set themselves
up, one might say, as co-arrangers of the universe. In fact, the new
science led away from immediate experience in the manner criticized by
Aristotle. Let us consider the understanding of the planetary motions.
Immediate experience teaches that the earth is at rest and that the sun
goes around it. In the more precise terms of our own day, we might even
say that the word “rest” is defined by the statement that the earth is
at rest, and that we call every body at rest that no longer moves
relative to the earth. If the word “rest” is understood in this
fashion—and it generally &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; so understood—then Ptolemy was right and
Copernicus was wrong. Only if we reflect upon the concepts of “motion”
and “rest,” and realize that motion implies a statement about the
relationship between at least two bodies, can we reverse the
relationship, making the sun the still center of the planetary system,
and thereby obtaining a far simpler and more unified picture of the
solar system, whose explanatory power was later fully recognized by
Newton. Copernicus has thus appended to immediate experience a wholly
new element, which I shall describe at this point as the “simplicity of
natural laws,” and which, in any event, has nothing to do with immediate
experience. That same can be seen in Galileo's laws of falling bodies.
Immediate experience teaches that light bodies fall more slowly than
heavy ones. Galileo maintained, on the contrary, that in a vacuum all
bodies fall with equal speed, and that their fall could be correctly
described by mathematically formulable laws, namely the Galilean laws of
falling bodies. But motion in a vacuum was at that time still quite
impossible to observe. The place of immediate experience, has therefore
been taken by an idealization of experience, which claims to be
recognized as the correct idealization by virtue of the fact that it
allows mathematical structures to become visible in the phenomena. There
can be no doubt that in this early phase of modern science the newly
discovered conformity to mathematical law has become the true basis for
its persuasive power. These mathematical laws, so we read in Kepler, are
the visible expression of the divine will, and Kepler breaks into
enthusiasm at the fact that he has been the first here to recognize the
beauty of God's work. Thus the new way of thinking assuredly had nothing
to do with any turning away from religion. If the new discoveries did in
fact contradict the teachings of the Church at certain points, this
could have little significance, seeing that it was possible to perceive
with such immediacy the workings of God in nature. The God here referred
to is, however, and ordering God, of whom we do not at once know whether
He is identical with the God to whom we turn in trouble, and to whom we
can relate our life. It may therefore be said, perhaps, that here
attention was directed entirely to one aspect of the divine activity,
and that hence there arose the danger of losing sight of the totality,
the interconnected unity of the whole; attention is too much drawn to
the narrow field of material welfare, and the other foundations of our
existence are neglected. Even if technology and science could be
employed merely as means to an end, the outcome depends upon whether the
goals for whose attainment they are to be used are good ones. But the
decision upon goals cannot be made within science and technology; it is
made, if we are not to go wholly astray, at a point where out vision is
directed upon the whole man and the whole of his reality, not merely on
a small segment of this. But this total reality contains much of which
we have not said anything yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there is the fact that man can develop his mental and spiritual
powers only in relation to a human society. The very capacities that
distinguish him above all other living creatures, the ability to reach
beyond the immediate sensory given, the recognition of wider
interrelations, depend upon his being lodged in a community of speaking
and thinking beings. History teaches that such communities have acquired
in their development not only an outward but also a spiritual pattern.
And in the spiritual patterns known to us, the relation to a meaningful
connection of the whole, beyond what can be immediately seen and
experienced, has almost always played the deciding role. It is only
within this spiritual pattern, of the ethos prevailing in the community,
that man acquires the points of view whereby he can also shape hes own
conduct wherever it involves more than a mere reaction to external
situations; it is here that the question about values is first decided.
Not only ethics, however, but the whole cultural life of the community
is governed by this spiritual pattern. Only within its sphere does the
close connection first become visible between the good, the beautiful,
and the true, and here only does it first become possible to speak of
life having a meaning for the individual. This spiritual pattern we call
the religion of the community. The word “religion” is thereby endowed
with a rather more general meaning than is customary. It is intended to
cover the spiritual content of many cultures and different periods, even
in places where the very idea of God is absent. Only in the communal
modes of thought pursued in modern totalitarian states, in which the
transcendent is completely excluded, would it be possible to doubt
whether the concept of religion can still be meaningfully applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we also recognize the characteristic difference between
genuine religions, in which the spiritual realm, the central spiritual
order of things, plays a decisive part, and the narrower forms of
thought, especially in our own day, which relate only to the strictly
experience-able pattern of a human community. Such forms of thought
exist in the liberal democracies of the West no less than in the
totalitarian states of the East. Here, too, to be sure, an ethic is
formulated, but the talk is of a norm of ethical behavior, and this norm
is derived from a world outlook, that is, from inspection of the
immediately visible world of experience. Religion proper speaks not of
norms, however, but of guiding ideals, by which we should govern our
conduct and which we can at best only approximate. These ideals do not
spring from inspection of the immediately visible world but from the
region of the structure lying behind it, which Plato spoke of as the
world of Ideas, and concerning which we are told in the Bible, “God is a
spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all that has here been said about religion is naturally well known;
it has been repeated only in order to emphasize that &lt;em&gt;even the natural
scientist must recognize this comprehensive significance of religion in
human society&lt;/em&gt;, if he wants to try to think about the relation of
religious and scientific truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already sought to enunciate the thesis that in the images and
likenesses of religion, we are dealing with a sort of language that
makes possible and understanding of that interconnection of the world
which can be traced behind the phenomena and without which we could have
no ethics or scale of values. This language is in principle replaceable,
like any other; in other parts of the world there are and have been
other languages that provide for the same understanding. But we are born
into a particular linguistic area. This language is closer akin to that
of poetry than to the precision-orientated language of natural science.
Hence the words in the two languages often have different meanings. The
heavens referred to in the Bible have little to do with the heavens into
which we send up aircraft and rockets. In the astronomical universe, the
earth is only a minute grain of dust in one of the countless galactic
systems, but for us it is the center of the universe—it really is the
center. Science tries to give its concepts an objective meaning. But
religious language must avoid this very cleavage of the world into its
objective and its subjective sides; for who would dare claim the
objective side to be more real than the subjective? &lt;em&gt;Thus we ought not
to intermingle the two languages&lt;/em&gt;; we should think more subtly than we
have hitherto been accustomed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The care to be taken in keeping the two languages, religious and
scientific, apart from one another, should also include an &lt;em&gt;avoidance of
any weakening of their content by blending them&lt;/em&gt;. The correctness of
tested scientific results cannot rationally be cast in doubt by
religious thinking, and conversely, the ethical demands stemming from
the heart of religious thinking ought not to be weakened by all too
rational arguments from the field of science. There can be no doubt, in
this connection, that through the enlargement of technical possibilities
new ethical problems have also appeared that cannot be easily resolved.
I may mention as examples the problem of the researcher's responsibility
for the practical application of his discoveries, or the still more
difficult question from the field of modern medicine of how long a
doctor should or may prolong the life of a dying patient. Consideration
of such problems has nothing to do with any watering down of ethical
principles. Nor am I able to conceive that such questions are capable of
being answered by pragmatic considerations of expediency alone. On the
contrary, here too it will be necessary to take into account the
connection of the whole—the source of ethical principles in that basic
human attitude which is expressed in the language of religion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, moreover, we may already be able to effect a more correct
distribution of the emphases that have been misplaced by the enormous
expansion of science and technology in the past hundred years. I mean
the emphases we ascribe to the material and the spiritual preconditions
in the human community. The material conditions are important, and it
was the duty of society to eliminate the material privation of large
sections of the population, once technology and science has made it
possible to do so. But now that this has been done, much unhappiness
remains, and we have come to see how compellingly the individual also
has need, in his self-consciousness or self-understanding, for the
protection the spiritual pattern of a community can provide. It is here,
perhaps, that our most important tasks now lie. If there is much
unhappiness among today's student body, the reason is not material
hardship, but the lack of trust that makes it too difficult for the
individual to give his life a meaning. We must try to overcome the
isolation which threatens the individual in a world dominated by
technical expediency. Theoretical deliberations about questions of
psychology or social structure will avail us little here, so long as we
do not succeed in finding a way back, by direct action, to a natural
balance between the spiritual and material conditions of life. It will
be a matter of reanimating in daily life the values grounded in the
spiritual pattern of the community, of endowing them with such
brilliance that the life of the individual is again automatically
directed toward them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is not my business to talk about society, for we were supposed to
be discussing the relationship of scientific and religious truth. In the
past hundred years, science has made very great advances. The wider
regions of life, of which we speak in the language of our religion, may
thereby have been neglected. We do not know whether we shall succeed in
once more expressing the spiritual form of our future communities in the
old religious language. A rationalistic play with words and concepts is
of little assistance here; the most important preconditions are honesty
and directness. But since ethics is the basis for the communal life of
men, and ethics can only be derived from that fundamental human attitude
which I have called the spiritual pattern of the community, we must bend
all our efforts to reuniting ourselves, along with the younger
generation, in a common human outlook. I am convinced that we can
succeed in this if again we find the right balance between the two kinds
of truth.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="linguistics"></category><category term="mysticism"></category><category term="physics"></category><category term="quantum physics"></category><category term="truth"></category><category term="Werner Heisenberg"></category></entry></feed>