<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Pelican Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/travel.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2013-03-25T13:38:00Z</updated><entry><title>Zeppelins, Chinese Junk Rigs, and Surfboards</title><link href="/zeppelins-chinese-junk-rigs-and-surfboards.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-25T13:38:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2013-03-25:zeppelins-chinese-junk-rigs-and-surfboards.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the first times I met up with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/moxie"&gt;Moxie&lt;/a&gt; while travelling, we met at a dive
bar in San Francisco's Mission District, packed with hipsters. I had nineteen years, a
modified state ID card, and just hitchhiked into town. We sat at the bar, and both ordered well gin and tonics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="junk" src="/static/images/2013/03/sboc/junk.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a proposal, the sort of get-rich-quick scheme it seems that only 18th century pirates and lazy hacker-squatters are capable of contriving: We fly to China. Then, we spend a few grand purchasing a Chinese junk rig, and equip it with a system of pulleys so that we can man the sails from the cockpit, solo if necessary. Next, we fill the cabin with about as much potable water as we can carry and enough dried food to stave off starvation, and set a course across the northern arc of the Pacific -- avoiding the treachery of the South Seas -- for San Francisco. The choice of vessel was key, the battoned sails and flattened hull of a Chinese junk rig make it arguably one of the safest ships to make a transoceanic voyage alone, not to mention the finicial incentives: being rare in the Americas, a well-kept junk rig would go for anywhere from $50,000 to $250,000 USD -- not to mention grant you free slip fees at just about any marina from Anchorage to Punta Arenas. How could anyone turn down such a preposterous plot which included adventure on the high seas, a high mortality risk, riches and notoriety?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I recall, Moxie shook and hung his head, and smiling countered my proposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Ever heard of Santos Dumont?" he asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Nope."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"So. Santos Dumont was a Brazilian hero, originally a Frenchman. This was around the late 1800s. He was the type of dude who would trek across the Amazon alone, leave for the North Pole with a party of eight and return with a party of three -- your standard gentleman-adventurer, a total madman. Sometime around the turn of the century, he returns to Paris to participate in a race to sail zeppelins from a certain point around the Eifel Tower and back. He wins, but being rich already, gives half the money to charity. The other half of the prize he puts in the care of a trust fund with the instructions that it should be awarded to anyone who can beat his time -- thirty minutes or so, from what I remember."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"No one's won it yet?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I'm not entirely sure, but the story appears to end there -- at least, there is no record of anyone claiming the money in the trust -- and it's been sitting there, collecting interest, for over a century now." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moxie swept the dreads out of his face, took a sip of the gin, and continued: "It should be simple to beat the time given the advantages of modern materials..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He and I have had a friendly series of bets throughout our friendship. Moxie usually wins...and I usually forget to name my stakes. I should have bet on this: If ever anyone were to be the cause for my going to the North Pole, it would be Moxie. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I awoke this morning in my underwear on top of a snarled mess of sheets, with my head rather uncomfortably hanging off the edge of the bed, two laptops and three android android phones¹ piled on top of and around me. The rhythmic pink-noise crash of surf was drafting in on sticky air through an open window above my face. I opened my eyes. Knots of lime-coloured vines hung from a tamarind tree with dark beanpods of fruit half a meter long. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="tamarind" src="/static/images/2013/03/sboc/tamarind.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Qu'est-que fuck? How did I get to Yavin IV?&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I blinked, expecting the familiar snowy silence of Prenzlauerburg to replace the acerbic green foliage, the clockwork clacking of the yellow U-Bahn cars across the raised tracks to replace the steady sound of waves...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="prenzlauerberg" src="/static/images/2013/03/sboc/eberswalderstrasse-prenzlauerberg-hinterof.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nope. Still on Yavin IV.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I remembered the dark curls hanging over noetic eyes and »à plus« on a trainstation platform in the French Alps, the two-hour search and interrogation by US customs agents in the basement of the Montrèal airport, talking all night with expat Iranian dissident-hackers and deciphering the pyobfsproxy stacktraces and kanji showing up in my terminal at the Tor developer meeting at Harvard, and then the series of flights which brought me to the longitudinal apogee of my starting point five days ago. The shortest path of return is straight down; the fastest takes me &lt;a href="http://www.distance.to/Honolulu_Berlin"&gt;directly over the North Pole&lt;/a&gt;. Damnit, should've made that bet...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the bets I lost years ago -- I think this one was the cost of my hubristic belief that I could pick a lock faster than Moxie -- had the stakes "loser has to go surfing naked". I still haven't paid that debt, but, having been on a surf team as a kid, I bet that, wetsuit or otherwise, I could surf better than he could. I think I forgot to name my stakes again, but it doesn't matter because I had to let Moxie off the hook this time, due to the painful complications of his recent knee surgery. Though, while waiting for the others to arrive, Christine, Moxie, and I did get a chance to to test out the small surf in our front yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't had to write any Java yet, and, tragically, my watercolour portait of &lt;a href="http://www.novosti.rs/upload/images/2011/03/3003j/james-gosling-java.jpg"&gt;James Arthur Gosling&lt;/a&gt; was confiscated at U.S. Customs in Montrèal, but I did write about twelve pages of equations in an attempt to sort out an elliptic curve MQV variation, changed to add embedded, deniable, and authenticated, key exchanges for both a long-term identity key and ephemeral session key as per Ian Goldberg et.al.'s denAKE() algorithm in the &lt;a href="http://www.cypherpunks.ca/~iang/pubs/mpotr.pdf"&gt;Multi-Party Off-The-Record paper&lt;/a&gt;. That'll get added to &lt;a href="https://github.com/isislovecruft/mpOTR"&gt;my fork of a collaborative MPOTR spec&lt;/a&gt; git repo shortly, and review by cryptologists is greatly appreciated. I also rooted my newly-acquired (for &lt;a href="https://ooni.torproject.org/"&gt;OONI&lt;/a&gt; mobile development testing and reading &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/"&gt;arxiv&lt;/a&gt; papers) android jellybean tablet, and finally ate the taco and tapatio-coated mango I'd been craving in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.patternsinthevoid.net"&gt;isis&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/isislovecruft"&gt;agora&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/isislovecruft"&gt;lovecruft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lahaina, Maui, Hawaii, United States&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24 March 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¹ Well, actually, one of them was a mozilla boot-to-gecko developer phone.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Spring Break of Code"></category><category term="Whispersys"></category></entry><entry><title>Rio de Janeiro</title><link href="/rio-de-janeiro.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-05-29T12:58:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2012-05-29:rio-de-janeiro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fourteen year old boy tries to sell me a ride in his cab for twice the
price. I take another cab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the federal police are smaller than I, but a group of them size me up
with amusement in their eyes. Last year, they killed thirteen hundred people
in this city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shirtless men wander on the freeway, selling pele porco frita between the
cars.
Others ride 100cc dirt bikes with furniture stacked on the back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unbridled horse eats trash in a field surrounded by favelas with
sun-bleached coloured sheets for roofs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a white cathedral on a distant hill, and vultures circling over an
open crude oil pit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That infamous captain of zeppelins, Santos-Dumont, built an enchanted house
somehwere in those hills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cab breaks down. The driver pulls over and &lt;em&gt;cranks the engine&lt;/em&gt;, cursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impossible black crags rise above the visible heat waves from the distant
jungle. I feel stupid: twenty hours in a flying sardine can, and now the
humidity -- I can't give the species name for any of the plants in sight, and
my Portuguese vocabulary is three: sim, não, &amp;amp; obrigarda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the dead of winter here, but you'd never know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah wait, that's a jacaranda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There appears to be a statue on a distant mountain: a robed white figure
raising arms and face to the cloudless azure sky. Fleets of teal, red, and
ochre sailboats scatter on the lagoon beneath a cablecar dangling between two
cliffs rising out of the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[![1]][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just arrived for &lt;a href="https://www.rightscon.org/rio/"&gt;RightsCon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://guardianproject.info/freebird/"&gt;Freebird&lt;/a&gt;, and also to meet with
two friends to discuss how we'll spend the the rest of this year working on
&lt;a href="http://ooni.nu/"&gt;OONI&lt;/a&gt;. I'm going to go explore now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[![1]]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/christ-the-redeemer11.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freebird"></category><category term="Guardian Project"></category><category term="OONI"></category><category term="RightsCon"></category><category term="Rio de Janeiro"></category><category term="Tor"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Viennese Cathedrals &amp; Sleepy Hollow</title><link href="/viennese-cathedrals-sleepy-hollow.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-22T00:24:00Z</updated><author><name>isis</name></author><id>tag:,2012-01-22:viennese-cathedrals-sleepy-hollow.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of the prettier places I've visited recently. I need to start making
a better effort at photodocumentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/wtf_wien.jpeg" title="wtf_wien" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_crypt.jpeg" title="sleepy_hollow_crypt" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_vault1.jpeg" title="sleepy_hollow_vault" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_train_bridge.jpeg" title="sleepy_hollow_train_bridge" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/wtf_wien.jpeg" title="wtf_wien" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/wtf_wien.jpeg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_crypt.jpeg" title="sleepy_hollow_crypt" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_crypt.jpeg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_vault1.jpeg" title="sleepy_hollow_vault" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_vault1.jpeg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_train_bridge.jpeg" title="sleepy_hollow_train_bridge" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/sleepy_hollow_train_bridge.jpeg&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="cathedral"></category><category term="gothic"></category><category term="graveyard"></category><category term="sleepy hollow"></category><category term="vienna"></category></entry><entry><title>Italia</title><link href="/italia.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-09T23:14:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2012-01-09:italia.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm sitting in a cottage in the Italian countryside outside Florence,
eating a breakfast of cafe brewed in an antique mocha, fette biscottate
con riso with vegan hazelnutella and arance amare, a spread of bitter
oranges. Outside the lead-paned window with iron fittings, I can see
hills covered with vineyards, and a haze of clouds below covers a snowy
valley with forested mountains in the distance. The floors and roof are
both constucted of bricks and timbers, and a castlemonte woodstove
creaks and crackles behind me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night I shared a sleeping compartment on a night train from Munich
with four noisy Estonians and a cute Italian hacker boy, who cuddled
next to me reading white papers on homomorphic cryptography. He works on
Tor, and also writes screenplays and acted in an Italian television
series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hiked through the countryside, through olive orchards, practicing
mentalist magic on kachi trees with rotten fruits, daring them to drop
to the ground. We marched through the keep of a fortress older than the
country I was born in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to go home. Or rather, I've rediscovered that my home is a
terrible place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome2-1024x768.jpg" title="arturorome2" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[\&amp;lt;3][] &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VJKX9Z86WuY"&gt;\&amp;lt;3&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hVHjwAwZdNk&amp;amp;feature=BFp&amp;amp;list=PL17D01C49099D0F12"&gt;\&amp;lt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome11-1024x768.jpg" title="arturorome11" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome10-1024x768.jpg" title="arturorome10" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/rome8-1024x768.jpg" title="rome8" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome2-1024x768.jpg" title="arturorome2" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome2.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome11-1024x768.jpg" title="arturorome11" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome11.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome10-1024x768.jpg" title="arturorome10" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/arturorome10.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/rome8-1024x768.jpg" title="rome8" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/rome8.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackers"></category><category term="italia"></category><category term="Tor"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Journey to the End of the Night</title><link href="/journey-to-the-end-of-the-night.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-04T02:55:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2012-01-04:journey-to-the-end-of-the-night.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Berlin, on New Year's Eve, I participated in a race through the
streets of Berlin, called Journey to the End of the Night -- except this
one, being at the end of the year, is called &lt;a href="http://totheendoftheyear.com/"&gt;Journey to the End of the
Year&lt;/a&gt;. The rules: run through six checkpoints in order, complete a
challenge at each one, and don't get caught by the chasers or lose your
armband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I formed a running team with &lt;a href="http://hellais.wordpress.com/"&gt;an Italian hacker who works on Tor&lt;/a&gt;, and
his friend from Greece who is also a hacker. They showed up thirty
minutes late (for which the organizers, my friends &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/#!/fin"&gt;from Vienna&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/#!/Rubin110"&gt;San Francisco&lt;/a&gt;, postponed the race) with a backpack full of
explosives. Let me tell you: Berliners take their fireworks &lt;em&gt;very
seriously&lt;/em&gt;, and firework safety inversely so. It's not uncommon at all
for a complete stranger to throw the equivalent of a quarter stick of
dynamite &lt;em&gt;at your face&lt;/em&gt;. Also, I noticed that Berliners like to
surprise you by throwing bottles and chairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, armed to the teeth with explosives, we set out running through the
streets with others chasing us. Because there was a joke rule that my
friend Redbeard's beard was a safe zone, I ended up having to kidnap him
from a checkpoint by aiming explosives at the other participants in the
race, and a few of the organizers too. Redbeard is awesome. He's a
professional kernel hacker with a red beard down to his waist, if the
later wasn't obviously by the name. I also had to dodge the
aforementioned chairs, bottles, and fireworks with parkour while wearing
a tinfoil hat. And at the end of it all, I found myself at &lt;a href="http://c-base.org/"&gt;C-Base&lt;/a&gt;, a
hackerspace built into the remains of a two-millenia-old alien spaceship
crash], discussing DIY soldering iron buttprobes, theoretical physics,
and hackers on sailboats, while drinking Chink Chank Chunk (Club Mate
with sugar, lime, vodka).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh Berlin, how I want to live in you!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Pathwork II</title><link href="/pathwork-ii.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-10-31T15:00:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2010-10-31:pathwork-ii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Again, my humble apologies for straying off topic and off the map.
Topic, topology, ideogeography. In Hakim Bey's words: "Art project: the
construction of a 'map' bearing a 1:1 ratio of the territory explored."
Sorry for rambling, sorry for wandering. Peregrinations behoove us, and
my oh my is inertia a motherfucker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery link="file" orderby="rand"]&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Pathwork</title><link href="/pathwork.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-26T19:25:00Z</updated><author><name>isis agora lovecruft</name></author><id>tag:,2010-09-26:pathwork.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wish to apologize in advance as this post really has nothing
whatsoever to do with physics, metaphysics, or anything really. I just
wanted somebody else to be able to appreciate the places I've seen in my
recent wanderings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-11-1024x341.jpg" title="Sunrise on Docks" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-2-1024x1024.jpg" title="Forest for The Trees" /&gt;][]&lt;em&gt;As the practiser looks exhaustively into discrimination and
it becomes void, he will wipe out birth and death but will not yet
attain Nirvana. If he clings to his knowledge of his all-embracing
consciousness and so sets up his own interpretation that all grass and
plants are sentient and do not differ from men and that after death men
will become grass and plants; if he delights in such misconception, he
will fall into error...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;- Surangama Sutra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above statement may be true, but that does not imply that the
converse is false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit, 6 October 2010:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Panorama-1024x240.jpg" title="No School" /&gt;][][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-12-1024x486.jpg" title="Abandoned School, Kent, TX" /&gt;][][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/1002_0224-1024x768.jpg" title="Sailing" /&gt;][]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-21-1024x566.jpg" title="Higgins, Mississippi" /&gt;][][][&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/1002_0224-1024x768.jpg" title="Sailing" /&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-11-1024x341.jpg" title="Sunrise on Docks" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-11.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-2-1024x1024.jpg" title="Forest for The Trees" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-2.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Panorama-1024x240.jpg" title="No School" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Panorama.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-12-1024x486.jpg" title="Abandoned School, Kent, TX" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-12.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/1002_0224-1024x768.jpg" title="Sailing" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/1002_0224.jpg
  [&lt;img alt="" src="http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-21-1024x566.jpg" title="Higgins, Mississippi" /&gt;]: http://www.patternsinthevoid.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Collage-21.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>